<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A curse become a blessing: or, A sermon preached in the parish church of S. John the Baptist, in the Ile of Thannet, in the country of Kent, at the funerall of that vertuous and worthy gentleman Mr. Paul Cleybrooke Esquire. By William Stone preacher of Gods word: on Tuesday, September 17. 1622</title>
            <author>Stone, William, preacher of Gods word.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23288</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106188</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841910</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841910</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6526</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12995)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1336:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A curse become a blessing: or, A sermon preached in the parish church of S. John the Baptist, in the Ile of Thannet, in the country of Kent, at the funerall of that vertuous and worthy gentleman Mr. Paul Cleybrooke Esquire. By William Stone preacher of Gods word: on Tuesday, September 17. 1622</title>
                  <author>Stone, William, preacher of Gods word.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 57, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland for William Sheffard, and are to be sold at his shop at the entring in of Popes-head Alley out of Lombard street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect; print show-through, some leaves cropped at head, and several pages stained; title page stained so as to be illegible. Beginning-page 15 from British Library copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:33"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:33"/>
            <p>A Curſe become a Bleſsing: OR, A SERMON PREACHED IN the Pariſh Church of <hi>S. John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> in the Ile of <hi>Thannet,</hi> in the County of KENT, at the Funerall of that vertuous and worthy Gentleman M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. PAVL CLEYBROOKE Eſquire.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM STONE Preacher of Gods Word: on Tueſday, September 17. 1622.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REVEL. 14.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, from henceforth, yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their workes doe follow them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Haviland</hi> for <hi>William Sheffard,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the entring in of Popes-head Alley out of <hi>Lombard ſtreet.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:34"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:34"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL AND VERTVOVS GENTLEWO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Miſtris MARY CLEY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BROOKE: <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere there nothing elſe to proue that the death of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that is, of euery beleeuing and repentant ſinner, is a moſt excellent bleſſing of God, euen this were ſufficient, that it <hi>is pretious in Gods ſight.</hi> For what can befall to the deare children of God, which is an excellent bleſſing of his vnto them, if that for one bee not ſuch a bleſſing, of which he ſaith, that it is <hi>preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in his ſight?</hi> Of all terrible things, death ſeemes moſt terrible, but it is not ſo indeed to them that be in Chriſt, to whom many things happen more bitter and heauy than death it ſelfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:35"/>
            <p>This Sermon, being a little enlarged, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that which was deliuered, in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter points of the text, I preſent vnto you, to whom of right it belongs. It is all that I am able to offer vnto you, in token of my thankfulneſſe for the loue and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes both of the dead, and of the liuing. Accept it, I beſeech you, &amp; reade it at your leiſure; and I pray God to bleſſe this little mite, that it may both further your preſent comfort, and the ſaluation of your ſoule.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in the Lord, <hi>WILLIAM STONE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:35"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, thou haſt here in few words, the definitiue ſentence of the Holy Ghoſt, touching the death of the Saints, that <hi>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi> From which, after the expoſition and diuiſion of the Text, is obſerued; first, that there be Saints vpon earth: Secondly, that theſe ſame Saints be liable to bodily death: Thirdly, that they be the Lords, and that after a ſpeciall manner: And fourthly, that their death is precious: which being further confirmed by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord, is both comfortable to them that mourne, and directs euery one how to iudge aright of all things and euents. Pray, reade, meditate, and practiſe, and the Lord giue the increaſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>December <hi>5. 1622.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
               <signed>W. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:36"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6526:36"/>
            <head>A FVNERALL SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALME 116.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Precious in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of his Saints.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I ſay any thing of the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this our meeting, let vs firſt conſider this preſent Text, and the inſtructions thereof: <hi>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a matter of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and a ground of no ſmall comfort, to vnderſtand aright, what to hold of the death of the Saints. For to the vngodly it ſeemes a very jeſt and a laughing ſport. They are glad to ſee the death of the beſt men, and moſt zealous, becauſe then they thinke that all things ſhall goe preſently as they deſire to haue it. And to the godly themſelues, it ſeemes fearefull and miſerable for the preſent time.</p>
            <p>Now touching this matter, the ſentence of the Holy Ghoſt is propounded vnto vs, in the words which yee haue heard, to this effect: That it is precious in Gods ſight. <hi>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:6526:37"/>
            <p>In handling this Text, both for helpe of memory, and plaineneſſe ſake, I will obſerue this method; firſt, declare the meaning of the words. Secondly, ſhew the parts thereof. And laſtly, handle the ſeuerall inſtructions from thence ariſing.</p>
            <p>In giuing the meaning of the words, I will follow the order of the Text, firſt declaring them ſeuerally, as they lye in the Text, and then gather into one ſumme that which hath beene ſaid, both plainly and briefly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precious.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Precious.</note>] The originall word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>jakar,</hi> which the <hi>Septuagint</hi> tranſlate moſt commonly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">n="a" 1 Sam. 3.1. 2 Sam. 12.30. 1 King. 5.17. and 7.9, 10, 11.</note> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">n="b" Iob 28.10. Pſal. 72.14. Prou. 20.15. Iſai. 43.4.</note>, which ſignifie <hi>precious;</hi> once <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">n="c" Zach. 11.13.</note>, <hi>approued;</hi> once <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">n="d" Ezek. 28.13.</note>, <hi>profitable, good,</hi> or <hi>commodious;</hi> and once <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">n="e" Prou. 1.13.</note> of great <hi>price</hi> and <hi>worth.</hi> In our Engliſh Bibles of the new Tranſlation, it is rendred moſt commonly, <hi>precious</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="f" 1 Sam. 3.1. and 26.21. Prou. 3.15. and 6.26. and 12.27. and 20.15. and 24.4.</note>; ſometimes, <hi>coſtly</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="g" 1 King. 5.17. and 7.9, 10, 11.</note>; once, <hi>noble</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="h" Ezra 4.10.</note>; once, <hi>better</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="i" Eccleſ 9.18.</note>; and once, <hi>goodly</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="k" Zach. 11.13. <hi>In the ſight.</hi>
               </note>. Neither can I but remember what one hath noted, ſaying; <hi>Dicitur autem pretioſum, quod ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; non omnibus obuium eſt;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>That thing is called precious, which is rare, and not to be met with of all.</hi> Out of this I gather, that <hi>Precious</hi> in this place is as much to ſay, as <hi>of great eſteeme, an excellent thing, exceeding profitable, good</hi> and <hi>honourable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the ſight;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>begnene.</hi> The Hebrew ſignifieth, <hi>in the eyes.</hi> Properly the <hi>Eye</hi> is that member of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, whoſe faculty is to ſee lightſome things, and to direct our way. Now diuers members of the body of man are attributed to God, as <hi>the head, the hands, the heart, the feet,</hi> and here, <hi>the eyes;</hi> but not properly, but figuratiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for properly God hath no ſuch members.<note place="margin">The eyes of God.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>The Eyes</hi> of God doe ſignifie, either firſt, the good will and fauour of God<note place="margin">n="l" Pſal. 17.8. and 33.18. &amp; 34.15. 1 Pet. 3.12.</note>; as in that ſpeech of the Pſalmiſt: <hi>The eyes of the Lord are vpon the righteous:</hi> And of <hi>Iob</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="m" Iob 36.7.</note>; <hi>He withdraweth not his eyes from the righteous.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Or ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the prouidence of God<note place="margin">n="n" 2 Chro. 16.9.</note>; as in that ſpeech of <hi>Hanani</hi> the <hi>Seer,</hi> to <hi>Aſa</hi> King of <hi>Iudah; For the eyes of the Lord runne to and fro throughout the whole earth.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Or thirdly,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6526:37"/>the knowledge of God, that ſo wee might vnderſtand that God is not ignorant of any thing, but knoweth all things, both ſecret and apparant; paſt, preſent, and to come, as perfectly and throughly, as if he looked vpon them, and ſaw them with his eyes. Thus <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith: <hi>The eyes of the Lord are in euery place,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15.3.</note> 
               <hi>beholding the euill and the good.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Or elſe finally, the iudgement and account of God touching any thing whatſoeuer, as in this place, touching the death of the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſight of God.</note>But according to our Engliſh Tranſlation, not any member, but one of the outward ſenſes, is here attributed to God, to wit, <hi>the ſight;</hi> for it is ſaid, <hi>In the ſight of the Lord:</hi> but the meaning is all one. For the ſight of God hauing any of his owne workes for the obiect, ſignifieth his iudgement, account, and approuing of the thing. As God is ſaid to <hi>haue ſeene the light,</hi> that it was good,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.4.</note> that is to ſay, to haue iudged, accounted, and approued it to be good. But if it haue men and their doings for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, then it ſignifieth his perfect knowledge both of them and of their doings: As the Apoſtle ſaith;<note place="margin">Hebr. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>Neither is there any creature that is not manifeſt in his ſight: but all things are naked and opened vnto the eyes of him with whom we haue to doe.</hi> And ſo it is ſaid of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> that ſuch a one did right, and ſuch a one did euill <hi>in the ſight of the Lord.</hi> And thus we reade, that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of God, to wit, Ieſus Chriſt, ſpake vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> in a dreame, ſaying; <hi>I haue ſeene all that Laban doth vnto thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 31.12. Exod. 3.7. Prou. 15.3.</note> And when the Lord ſaid, <hi>I haue ſurely ſeene the affliction of my people which are in Egypt.</hi> In this ſenſe alſo <hi>the eyes of the Lord are</hi> ſaid to be <hi>in euery place, beholding the euill and the good.</hi> In this text which I haue now in hand, theſe words, <hi>in the ſight,</hi> be as much to ſay, as in the iudgement, eſteeme, and account of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>LORD</hi> in great letters.</note>
               <hi>Of the</hi> LORD. Yee finde (if yee marke it) the word LORD, written in this place, and in many places elſe in the Bibles of the new Tranſlation, in capitall or great letters: and likewiſe the word GOD, diuers times ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6526:38"/>printed, and namely in the Propheſie of <hi>Ezekiel.</hi> In all theſe places in the Hebrew, it is either <hi>Iah,</hi> or <hi>Iehouah,</hi> but moſt commonly <hi>Iehouah,</hi> as it is in this text. Except in a few places, where the Engliſh of <hi>Adonai, the</hi> LORD, is ſo written: as namely in the places quoted in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent<note place="margin">n="a" Gen. 18.27. Num. 14.17. Deu. 10.17. Ioſh. 7.8. Iudg. 13.8.2 King. 4.28.</note>. And likewiſe of <hi>Adon, the</hi> LORD, once in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachi</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="b" Mal. 3.1.</note>. And contrarily, the Engliſh of <hi>Iehouah, the Lord,</hi> is written in ſmall letters, in one place of <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> in ſome Bibles, in theſe words, <hi>The Lord of hoſtes in his name</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="c" Ier. 51.19. <hi>Printed Anno</hi> 1613. <hi>in</hi> 8. <hi>The names of God.</hi>
               </note>. And this might happen either through the Scribe, or the Printers fault.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The names of God</hi> in the Scripture be diuers, whereof ſome ſignifie the proprieties of his eſſence; as <hi>the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, the moſt High, the Holy one.</hi> And others the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eſſence it ſelfe: and theſe in the Hebrew text be three, <hi>Iehouah, Iah, Ehjeh;</hi> and may be rendred in Engliſh; <hi>God, the Lord, I Am,</hi> or, <hi>the Lord, the Lord, I Am.</hi> Here he is named <hi>Iehouah,</hi> by the firſt of theſe three. A name ſo proper to the Lord, that it is neuer attributed, nor can it agree to any of the creatures. As the Pſalmiſt ſaith; <hi>That men may know that thou,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 83.18.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe Name alone is Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah: art the moſt High ouer all the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What <hi>Iehouah</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies.</note>It ſignifieth three things; firſt, that God hath his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of himſelfe<note place="margin">n="d" Reu. 1.4. and 16.5.</note>: Secondly, that all creatures haue their being from him<note place="margin">n="e" Act. 17.28. Rom. 11.36.</note>: Thirdly, that he cauſeth all things to come to paſſe, according to his owne meaning, whether he promiſe or threaten. For this cauſe he addeth ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this ſpeech; <hi>And they ſhall know that I am Iehouah,</hi> or, <hi>that I am the Lord,</hi> to his promiſes<note place="margin">n="g" Ezek. 29.21. and 34.30.</note>, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings<note place="margin">n="h" Ezek. 7.27. and 12.15, 16. and 15.7. and 20.26. Iehouah <hi>vſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally,</hi> Pſal. 110.1. <hi>See alſo</hi> Pſal. 2.2.</note>.</p>
            <p>It is vſed two waies, either <hi>Perſonally,</hi> or <hi>Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Perſonally,</hi> to note one or two of the Perſons of the bleſſed Trinitie, as <hi>the Father,</hi> in this ſpeech; <hi>The Lord,</hi> in the originall, <hi>Iehouah,</hi> that is, <hi>the Father ſaid vnto my Lord,</hi> that is, vnto the Sonne, <hi>Sit thou at my right hand: vntill I make thine enemies thy foot-ſtoole.</hi> It notes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6526:38"/>
               <hi>the Sonne,</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith; <hi>And the Lord,</hi> in Hebrew,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.1.</note> 
               <hi>Ieheuah, appeared vnto him, in the plaines of Mamre.</hi> And it notes <hi>the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> in theſe words of <hi>Iſaiah; Holy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 6.3, 5.</note> 
               <hi>holy, holy, is the Lord of hoſtes.</hi> And againe, <hi>for mine eyes haue ſeene the King, the Lord of hostes.</hi> In both theſe ſpeeches, this word, <hi>the Lord,</hi> is in Hebrew <hi>Iehouah;</hi> and that it notes the Holy Ghoſt is plaine by this, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> alledging the ſame words, which the Lord in this place commands <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to tell the people, ſaith; <hi>Well ſpake the Holy Ghost by Eſaias the Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 28.25.</note> 
               <hi>vnto our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> And in this ſame place of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> it notes alſo the Sonne. As appeares by comparing it with that place in <hi>Saint Iohn,</hi> where he ſaith;<note place="margin">Iohn 12.41.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe things ſaid Eſaias, when he ſaw his glory, and ſpake of him.</hi> Sometimes alſo <hi>the Father</hi> and <hi>the Sonne</hi> are noted by this title, being twice vſed in one and the ſame verſe. As when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith; <hi>Then the Lord,</hi> that is, the Sonne,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.24.</note> 
               <hi>rained vpon So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and vpon Gomorrah, brimſtone and fire from the Lord,</hi> that is to ſay, from the Father, <hi>out of heauen.</hi> And againe, in <hi>Zechariah; And the Lord,</hi> that is, the Sonne,<note place="margin">Zech. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Satan; The Lord,</hi> that is, the Father, <hi>rebuke thee, O Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, euen the Lord,</hi> that is, the Father, <hi>that hath choſen Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem rebuke thee.</hi> In all theſe places the word tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>the Lord,</hi> is in the originall, <hi>Iehouah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iehouah</hi> vſed Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly.</note>Secondly, this word is vſed <hi>Eſſentially,</hi> to note God Almighty, one God in eſſence: as in this ſpeech of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah, The Lord Iehouah is my ſtrength and my ſong.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 12.2. &amp; 26.4.</note> And againe; <hi>Truſt yee in the Lord for euer: for in the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah is euerlaſting ſtrength.</hi> In this ſenſe it is taken, in theſe words of <hi>Dauid; Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The death.</hi> Vnderſtand by death here,<note place="margin">The death.</note> the death of the body, or temporall death, which is a priuation of the life of the body, by meanes of the locall ſeparating of the ſoule from it for a time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Againſt the Vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitaries.</note>I would haue this word well marked, that I ſay, <hi>by meanes of the locall ſeparating of the ſoule from the body.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:6526:39"/>For hereupon the death of Chriſt confuteth the <hi>Vbiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries,</hi> which hold that his body is euery where preſent. But if Chriſt died truly; if his death that he dyed vpon the croſſe were a true bodily death, then his body is not euery where: becauſe if it were euery where, and if it had beene euery where, at that time when it hung vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe, then his ſoule could not had beene lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſeparated from his body: but his ſoule was locally ſeparated from his body, or elſe he dyed not truly; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the body of Chriſt, nor yet his ſoule was not euery where then. And as it was then, ſo is it now; for his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is the ſame which then it was, and hath the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties which then it had. And if his body, nor yet his ſoule,<note place="margin">Of his Saints.</note> were not euery where then, neither be they euery where now. <hi>It followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of his Saints.</hi> The Hebrew word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidau;</hi> which is as much to ſay, as <hi>Of his deerely beloued ones;</hi> or, <hi>of his tender hearted, meeke, and mercifull ones;</hi> or, <hi>of them of whom he hath pittie, and on whom he hath mercy.</hi> For the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chaſid,</hi> importeth ſuch as to whom God ſheweth mercy, and ſo are made alſo to truſt and rely vpon his mercy and goodneſſe, and to ſhew themſelues pittifull, mercifull, and godly in their conuerſations. It occurres much oftner in the booke of the Pſalmes, than in all the reſt of the Bible. Moſt commonly it is tranſlated by the <hi>Septuagint</hi> in their Greeke tranſlation, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">n="a" Deut. 33.8. 2 Sam. 22.26. 2 Chron. 6.41. Pſal. 4.3. &amp; 12.1. &amp; 16.10. &amp; 18.25. &amp; 30.4. &amp; 31.23. &amp; 31.6. &amp; 37.28. &amp; 50.5. &amp; 52.9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>; <hi>holy;</hi> once <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">n="b" Pſal. 89.19.</note>, a <hi>Sonne;</hi> once <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">n="c" Mic. 7.2.</note>, <hi>venerable,</hi> or <hi>religious;</hi> and once <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">n="d" Pro. 2.8.</note>; <hi>reuerencing.</hi> In our Engliſh Bibles alſo of the new tranſlation, I finde it diuers waies tranſlated. Moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, <hi>Saints</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="e" 2 Chron. 6.41. Pſ. 30.4. &amp; 31.23. &amp; 37.28. &amp; 50.5. &amp; 52.9. &amp; 79 2. &amp; 85.8. &amp; 97.10. &amp; 132.9, 16. &amp; 145.10. &amp; 148.14. &amp; 149.1, 5, 9. Pro. 2.8.</note>; ſometimes, <hi>holy</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="f" Deut. 33.8. Pſal. 16.10. &amp; 86.2. &amp; 89.19. &amp; 145.17.</note>; thrice, <hi>godly</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="g" Pſa. 4.3. &amp; 12.1. &amp; 32.6.</note>; twice, <hi>mercifull</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="h" 2 Sam. 22.26. Pſal. 18.25.</note>; and once, <hi>the good man</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="i" Mic. 7 2.</note> Out of which I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that by <hi>Saints</hi> in this place, are meant Gods <hi>Elect and beloued children, effectually called, iuſtified, and ſanctified; people that are holy, righteous, ſober, and godly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus haue I gone thorow with the words of the text, taking word by word. Now let vs gather into one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6526:39"/>ſumme, the totall of the things which haue beene deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered touching the meaning thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precious,</hi> that is to ſay, of great eſteeme, very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and honourable, <hi>in the ſight of the Lord,</hi> that is to ſay, in the iudgement of the Lord, and in his account, <hi>is the death,</hi> that is, the bodily death, <hi>of his Saints,</hi> that is to ſay, of his elect, whom he hath called and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to whom he hath vouchſafed his ſpeciall fauour, and the grace to liue ſoberly, righteouſly, and godlily in this preſent world, denying vngodlineſſe and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I done with the firſt thing touching the meaning of the words. The ſecond followeth, touching <hi>the parts of the Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parts of the Text.</p>
            <p>THis Text hath two parts: Firſt, a propoſition or theme; ſecondly, an argument of confirmation, or a proofe thereof. <hi>The propoſition</hi> is this, that the death of the Saints is precious; <hi>precious is the death of his Saints. The proofe</hi> is in theſe words; <hi>in the ſight of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the propoſition</hi> there be two things to be conſidered; <hi>Firſt,</hi> the ſubiect or antecedent; <hi>Secondly,</hi> the attribute or conſequent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſubiect</hi> containes the matter whereof the ſpeech is; in theſe words of the text; <hi>The death of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The attribute</hi> ſhewes what is ſpoken of this matter, in theſe words; <hi>is precious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus haue I done with the ſecond branch of my promiſe. The third remaineth, which is concerning the inſtructions that ariſe from this Text, which I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound vnto you according to the order of the parts, as now yee haue heard them.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:6526:40"/>
            <p> The Inſtructions.</p>
            <p>FIrſt then I haue to begin with the propoſition, and namely with the ſubiect or antecedent thereof, in theſe words of the text, <hi>the death of the Saints.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let any man maruell, that I beginne with the laſt words of the text firſt. The learned doe ſee the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it. For the parts are inuerted in the order of the text. The proofe being inſerted betweene the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent and the antecedent; and both the conſequent and the proofe being ſet before the antecedent. But let the inuerted parts be placed in order, and the text ſtands thus: <hi>The death of his Saints,</hi> or, <hi>the death of the Saints is precious in the ſight of the Lord.</hi> In this order the parts doe plainly appeare; and this order muſt I follow.</p>
            <p>To proceede then with the ſubiect, <hi>the death of the Saints:</hi> firſt note this, that in the Scripture there is a twofold death attributed to the Saints; the one <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and the other, <hi>bodily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſpirituall death attributed to the Saints.</note>
               <hi>The ſpirituall death</hi> attributed to the Saints is likewiſe double, one <hi>before their calling,</hi> moſt miſerable and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; another <hi>after their calling,</hi> moſt bleſſed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Before their calling</hi> they are dead in ſinnes and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1, 4, 5.</note> As the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>And you hath he quickened who were dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes.</hi> And againe a little after; <hi>But God who is rich in mercy, for his great loue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he loued vs, Euen when we were dead in ſinnes, hath quickened vs together with Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">What death in ſinne, or ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all death is.</note> This ſpirituall death is a priuation of communion and fellowſhip with God, and of the grace of God quickening vs together with Chriſt: and is incident to the elect together with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate before their calling.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Three branches of ſpirituall death in the Saints.</note>But <hi>after their calling</hi> they haue experience in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of another manner of ſpirituall death, of which there be theſe three branches; firſt, vpon the right vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6526:40"/>of the doctrine of the Law to be brought to ſee and feele that they are dead and moſt wretched,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> A death at the comming of the commandement.</note> and that there is nothing in themſelues, ſaue matter of death and eternall damnation, by reaſon of their ſinnes; and ſo they are ſtirred vp to ſeeke ſuccour elſewhere. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> died; as he ſaith; <hi>But when the commandement came,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>ſinne reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and I died.</hi> That is to ſay, when I had the right vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the commandement of God, and had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered well of it, ſinne did rage and trouble my minde, which had lyen ſtill before, and by reaſon of my ſinne, I ſaw nothing in my ſelfe, but matter of death and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo I was driuen to ſeeke helpe in Ieſus Chriſt, that my ſoule might be ſaued.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Saints are dead to the Law;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> A death vnto the Law. <hi>Gal. 2.19.</hi>
               </note> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith; <hi>For I through the Law, am dead to the Law, that I might liue vnto God.</hi> The meaning is; they are freed from the dominion of the Law: and that by meanes of the Law it ſelfe, which accuſeth, terrifieth, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them, and thereby occaſioneth or vrgeth them to flie vnto Chriſt, which is the cauſe of this death. And they are dead to the Law, that is to ſay, they are free from the dominion of the Law in foure reſpects. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in reſpect of that moſt rigorous and ſeuere exacting of moſt perfect obedience to be performed in this life for the obtaining of life eternall.<note place="margin">Act. 15.10. Rom. 6.14, 15. and 7.6.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in reſpect of the curſe and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory ſentence of the Law for the breach therof, becauſe Chriſt being become a ſurety for vs, hath fulfilled that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act righteouſnes of the Law for vs, and performed that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience for vs, and for vs hath vndergone &amp; borne, yea and ouercome the curſe and puniſhment. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the power of the Law,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.8.</note> whereby as an occaſion it prouoketh &amp; ſtirreth vp the corruption of the hart in the vnregenerat. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, in reſpect of the obſeruation of the iudgements and ceremonies of the Law, that is,<note place="margin">Act. 15. 1 Cor. 9.1, 19. 2 Cor. 3.17. Heb. 9.10. Iohn 1.17.</note> of the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall and Ceremoniall Law, to wit, ſo farre, as they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly pertained only to the policy of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6526:41"/>of the ancient people and Church of God: ſuch as be the lawes concerning ſacrifices, and the whole out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip preſcribed by <hi>Moſes.</hi> But ſuch lawes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them as belong to the Law of Nature, and haue alwaies bound all Nations of the world, there is no death to them, nor no freeing therefrom.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> A death vnto ſin and the world.</note>Thirdly, there is a ſpirituall death which the Saints feele in themſelues, by which they die to ſinne and to the world, that is to ſay, by which they more and more bid ſinne farewell,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.31. Gal. 6.14.</note> and ſeuer themſelues from the men of this world, as much as poſſibly they can, by faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>This is a bleſſed death ſpringing from the death of Chriſt, by a vertue and power deriued therefrom for the beating downe and killing of the ſtrength of ſinne in vs that be his members. For that ſame diuine power, which ſupported his manhood ſo that he ſunke not, when hee ſtood charged with our ſinnes, and died for vs, and we in him; euen that ſame diuine power worketh in all his members for the mortifying of ſinne through his death. From whence it commeth that euery true beleeuer dieth more and more to ſinne continually. And this now can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be a moſt precious death in the ſight of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an effect of the death of his Sonne, of whom hee ſaith; <hi>This is my beloued Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed:</hi> and <hi>in whom he was</hi> (as the Apoſtle beares witneſſe) <hi>recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling the world vnto himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 3.17. 2 Cor. 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>not imputing their treſpaſſes vnto them.</hi> But neuertheleſſe it is not that death, which <hi>Dauid</hi> here meanes.</p>
            <p>We muſt therefore conſider that other kinde of death, which according to the Scripture the Saints be ſubiect vnto,<note place="margin">Bodily death attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Saints.</note> and that is the death of the bodie; of which I ſaid, that it is a priuation of the life of the bodie, by meanes of the locall ſeparating of the ſoule from the body fora time.</p>
            <p>This death of the bodie (as I conceiue) is the death which <hi>Dauid</hi> doth eſpecially meane in this place.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:6526:41"/>
            <p> The death of his Saints.</p>
            <p>FIrſt, this very mentioning of the death of the Saints, doth imply this much, which <hi>I</hi> note for the inſtruction of ſome ignorant and vnlearned people, that liue among vs, whom I deſire well to marke it, and to learne from this Sermon, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Doct.</hi> Some be Saints in this life: And namely all Gods people, euen all that be ſaued,<note place="margin">Gods people be all Saints before they die.</note> be Saints before their death. This very ſpeech, <hi>the death of his Saints,</hi> implieth thus much. And it is according to our Creed, in the ninth article whereof, we confeſſe that we beleeue <hi>the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Saints;</hi> which is not only to be vnderſtood of the Saints in heauen, but alſo of the Saints vpon earch. And thus the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul,</hi> for diuers of them, are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Saints. As the Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians; To the Saints which are at Epheſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.1. Philip. 1.1. Col. 1.2.</note> And the Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians; To all the Saints in Chriſt Ieſus which are at Philippi.</hi> And likewiſe the Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians; To the Saints and faithfull brethren in Chriſt, which are at Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſe.</hi> In all which places are vnderſtood by <hi>the Saints,</hi> Gods faithfull ſeruants then aliue vpon the earth. And as it was then, ſo is it now.<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.4. and 31.23. and 34.9 and 37.28. and 50.5. and 52.9. and 79.2. and 85 8. and 89.7. and 97.10. and 13 29, 16. and 145.10 and 148.14. and 149.1, 5, 9. Pſal. 16.3. Act. 9.13.</note> As many faithfull ſeruants as God hath amongſt mankind throughout the world, ſo many Saints there be liuing at this day vpon the earth. And in this ſenſe the word <hi>Saints,</hi> is taken aboue a dozen times in the booke of the Pſal. In one place whereof ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe mention is made of the Saints on earth. In the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Pſalme at the third verſe, be theſe words: <hi>But to the Saints that are in the earth.</hi> And in the Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; <hi>Ananias</hi> ſaith: <hi>Lord I haue heard by many of this man, how much euill he hath done to thy Saints at Ieruſalem.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe in the preſence of <hi>Agrippa</hi> declaring his life from his child-hood, hath theſe very words;<note place="margin">Act. 26.10.</note> 
               <hi>And many of the Saints did I ſhut vp in priſon.</hi> Which cannot poſſibly be taken otherwiſe, then of ſome that then were
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6526:42"/>aliue vpon the earth. And thus <hi>Aaron,</hi> while hee liued, and was enuied of ſome, is called <hi>the Saint of the Lord: They enuied Moſes alſo in the Campe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 106.16.</note> 
               <hi>and Aaron the Saint of the Lord.</hi> So that it is certaine, and as cleare as the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine, that there bee Saints in this world. If it were not ſo, there were no holy Catholike Church for vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue according to our Creed: nor any one man nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man liuing at this day vpon the face of the earth, that were the true childe of God.</p>
            <p>Queſtion. <hi>Who then bee the Saints now aliue vpon the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lambert in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes. cap. <hi>2.</hi> Parad. <hi>31,</hi> &amp; <hi>36.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Mac. hom. <hi>17.</hi> Why Gods children on earth be called Saints.</note> 
               <hi>Lambert</hi> ſhall tell thee: <hi>They bee Saints,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that be tranſlated from profane or worldly things, to godly and ſpirituall things, and made holy and conſecrated vnto God.</hi> And againe; <hi>All true faithfull people be Saints.</hi> Otherwiſe thus: Euerie man and woman that is effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called, and regenerated by the Holy Ghoſt, to liue iuſtly and holily; euerie ſuch is a Saint. And ſuch bee called <hi>Saints,</hi> not to note an abſolute perfection in them: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But firſt, becauſe they haue Chriſts holineſſe imputed vnto them through faith. For the holineſſe of Chriſt, that is to ſay, that integritie and puritie which Chriſt had from the firſt moment of his conception, and kept alſo in all his thoughts, words, and deeds, yea euen in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and thorowout his whole life, euen vnto his laſt end in the death of the croſſe, is part of that righteouſneſſe which is imputed vnto vs, by which wee are iuſtified. In this ſenſe the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.30.</note> 
               <hi>But of him are yee in Chriſt Ieſus, who of God is made vnto vs wiſdome, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſanctification, and redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, becauſe they haue inherent holines wrought by the Spirit in all the powers of their ſoule, and in euery part and member of their body. For ſanctification is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and thorowout the whole man; according to the Apoſtles prayer:<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>And the verie God of peace ſanctifie you wholly: and I pray God your whole ſpirit, and ſoule, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be preſerued blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6526:42"/>Chriſt.</hi> There is no part nor power of body or ſoule, but feeles the vertue of Gods Spirit purging away cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and faſtening impreſſions of holy qualities. It may bee this power of Gods ſanctifying Spirit appeares not alike euidently in euery part, yet hath euery particle his ſeaſoning with ſanctitie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, becauſe in imitation of the holineſſe of God, according to his Commandement:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>Bee yee holy, for I am holy:</hi> they labour to expreſſe holineſſe, both in their thoughts before God, and in their words and deeds before God and men. Becauſe it is written;<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>Follow peace with all men, and holineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, to diſtinguiſh them from all the world of the vngodly, which bee termed in Scripture;<note place="margin">Gal. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>This preſent euill world,</hi> and be ſaid all of them to lie in wickedneſſe, in theſe words of <hi>S. Iohn: Wee know that wee are of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>and the whole world lieth in wickedneſſe.</hi> Thus yee ſee who in the world be Saints, and why they be ſo called, being yet aliue vpon the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This ſerues to condemne that ignorant ſort, that all this while in the cleare light of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">To condemne their ignorance, that thinke there be no Saints vpon earth.</note> haue not learned thus much, that there be Saints vpon earth. Nay (as it ſeemes) ſome lie ſo plunged in this gulfe of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, that not only they doe not know that there bee Saints vpon earth, but that they dare breake out and ſay, that they will neuer beleeue it: <hi>I will neuer beleeue</hi> (ſaid one) <hi>that any be Saints vpon earth.</hi> Oh graceleſſe ſpeech I Oh damnable ignorance! I wiſh all you that heare this, be better inſtructed in this point. But marke what I ſay; I ſpeake it to thee, that art of the minde that there bee no Saints vpon earth. Thou thine owne ſelfe art either a Saint or a Deuill. And if thou be no Saint, thou haſt no faith in Chriſt. For none that hath faith in Chriſt, but he is a Saint. Againe, marke this, if thou bee not a Saint vpon earth before thou doeſt die, thou ſhalt neuer bee a Saint in heauen after thou art dead. And therefore, if thou wilt neuer beleeue that any bee Saints vpon earth, I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6526:43"/>will neuer beleeue that euer thou ſhalt bee a Saint in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For death doth ſanctifie none. Neither will God make any one a Saint in the kingdome of heauen, which was not before his death made a Saint vpon earth. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it, and receiue inſtruction.</p>
            <p>The death of his Saints.</p>
            <p>THere bee two or three things more to bee noted in theſe words;<hi>The death of his Saints:</hi> whereof one ariſeth as the former point from the very mentioning of the Saints death,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re ſubiect to death.</hi> Heb 9.27. and 11.13. Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note> and that is this, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Doct.</hi> The beſt men are liable to bodily death. The holieſt Saints that liue in the world muſt make this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that they ſhall one day die. The Apoſtle maketh no exception, when hee ſaith to the <hi>Hebrewes; It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed vnto men once to die.</hi> And of certaine of the Saints he ſaith; <hi>Theſe all died in faith.</hi> And <hi>Zechariah</hi> ſaith; <hi>Your fathers, where are they? And the Prophets, doe they live f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r euer?</hi> Death is the way of all the earth, as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid, when they were ready to die. <hi>And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, this day I am going the way of all the earth</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="a" Ioſh 23.14.</note>. And <hi>Dauid: I goe the way of all the earth</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="b" 1 King. 2.2.</note>. <hi>Adam</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="c" Gen. 5.5.</note>, <hi>Sheth</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="d" Gen. 5.8.</note>, <hi>Enoſh</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="e" Gen. 5.11.</note>, <hi>Cainan</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="f" Gen. 5.14.</note>, <hi>Mahalaleel</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="g" Gen. 5.17.</note>, <hi>Iared</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="h" Gen. 5.20.</note>, <hi>Methuſhelah</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="i" Gen. 5.27.</note>, <hi>Lamech</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="k" Gen. 5.31.</note>, <hi>Noah</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="l" Gen. 9.29.</note>; though their liues were long; for they liued all of them many hundreds of yeeres; yet they are dead and gone. Likewiſe <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="m" Gen. 25.8.</note> and <hi>Sarah</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="n" Gen. 23.2.</note>, <hi>Iſaac</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="o" Gen. 35.29.</note>, and <hi>Rebekah</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="p" Gen. 49.31.</note>, <hi>Iacob</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="q" Gen. 49.33.</note> and <hi>Rachel</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="r" Gen. 35.19.</note>, <hi>Iob</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="ſ" Iob 42.17.</note>, <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="t" 1 King. 2.10.</note>, <hi>Solomon</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="u" 1 King. 11.43.</note>, <hi>Hezekiah</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="*" 2 King. 20.21.</note>, <hi>Ioſiah</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="x" 2 Chro. 35.24.</note>, <hi>Samuel</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="y" 1 Sam. 25.1.</note>, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets<note place="margin">n="z" Ioh. 8.53.</note> are dead. All theſe were Saints, yet they haue taſted of deaths cup, with many thouſands more.</p>
            <p>Queſtion. <hi>But why ſhould the Saints die, ſeeing Chriſt hath died for them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It is true that Chriſt hath died for them: yet they muſt die. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe there is no ſuch end of Chriſts death,<note place="margin">The ends of Chriſts death.</note> as the freeing of the Saints from bodily death. For theſe be the ends of Chriſts death.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:6526:43"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to proue the truth of his manhood.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, that the faithfull Martyrs might haue true comfort againſt death, and know aſſuredly that it is no ſmall honour to them, to ſuffer for Chriſts ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, to ſanctifie our death, and to take away the ſting thereof, that we ſhould not doubt, but with comfort commend, and ſurrender vp our ſoules into the hands of God, whenſoeuer he doth call vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, to ratifie the eternall Teſtament and Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace.<note place="margin">Heb. 9.15, 16, 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, that through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> the Deuill.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, to deliuer vs from the feare of death.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seuenthly, that we alſo might die to ſinne,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.15.</note> and ſinne might not reigne in vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eighthly,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.11, 12.</note> that wee ſhould be Chriſts being married to him, as a wife to a ſecond husband after the death of the firſt.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.2, 3, 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninthly, that they which liue, ſhould not henceforth liue to themſelues, but vnto him which died for them,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.15.</note> and roſe againe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Tenthly, that we might know the loue of Chriſt vnto vs,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.16.</note> and publiſh it vnto others.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Eleuenthly, that whether we wake or ſleepe, we ſhould liue together with him.<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Twelfthly, that we ſhould not doubt to lay downe our liues for his ſake,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.16.</note> and the brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> Thirteenthly, that he might aboliſh ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Fourteenthly, that he might aboliſh death,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.10.</note> the wages of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Theſe bee the ends of the death of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.10.</note> but the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of the Saints from bodily death is none of them.</p>
            <p>Obiection. <hi>But if among the ends of Chriſts death this be reckoned for one,</hi> that he might aboliſh death, <hi>it ſeemeth then that the Saints ſhould not die. For what is it to aboliſh death, if it be not quite to take it away, that it ſhould not bee at all?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6526:44"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How death is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If ye vnderſtand it of death eternall, which is the ſecond death, it is quite taken away in reſpect of Gods elect: according to that ſpeech of our Sauiour Chriſt;<note place="margin">Iohn 11.26.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoeuer liueth and beleeueth in mee, ſhall neuer die.</hi> The ſecond death hath no power on the Saints. As ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 20.6.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed and holy is hee that hath part in the firſt reſurrection: on ſuch the ſecond death hath no power.</hi> But if ye referre it to the firſt death, to wit, the death of the body, the ſting of it is taken away, ſo that it is no more a curſe for the ſinnes which wee haue committed; nay it is turned into a bleſſing, and made a ioyfull paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and entrance into heauen. But if yee apply it to the death of the ſoule, which is another kinde, or another branch of the firſt death, that alſo is vanquiſhed &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and we recouer out of it, when we are ſpiritually quickned with the life of grace,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.11. Epheſ. 4.18.</note> called by <hi>S. Paul, the life of Ieſus, the life of God;</hi> and it is alſo called <hi>the life of the ſpirit.</hi> And though this death hang about vs, as long as we are in this tabernacle,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.23. Rom. 7.24.</note> and make vs groane within our ſelues, and crie out with the Apoſtle; <hi>O wretched man that I am: who ſhall deliuer mee from the body of this death?</hi> Yet it cannot hurt vs; and it daily abateth as the life of grace increaſeth. And when our change is come, we ſhall be fully and for euer diſcharged from it. For death is vanquiſhed, but the time is not yet come, that it muſt be vtterly deſtroyed. For the Apoſtle hath taught vs, that it is the laſt enemie that ſhall be deſtroyed;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.26.</note> 
               <hi>The laſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that ſhall be deſtroied, is death.</hi> It is capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated, and brought vnder the power of Chriſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, and comfort your ſelues, euery kinde of death ſhall be fully deſtroyed, and quite aboliſhed in the due time.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, the Saints muſt die the death of the body: becauſe it is an infirmity, which we are forced to endure in this nature. Now Chriſt hath not ſuffered to free vs from any infirmity to which our bodies are made ſubiect without ſinne, but to take away the venome of it, and to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6526:44"/>ſanctifie it vnto vs: that that which at firſt came by meanes of ſin, and in it ſelfe is a curſe for ſin, &amp; the wages thereof, may be turned into a bleſſed meanes to further our happineſſe. And thus alſo we are weary, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and thirſt, and feele paines many and manifold, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Chriſt alſo hath ſuffered all this for vs. Conceiue it then, that in reſpect of the Saints, death is aboliſhed both the firſt and ſecond, of the ſoule and the body, as it is the wages of ſinne, (for what haue we to doe with the wages of the workes, which we doe not attend?) but yet we muſt ſtill ſuffer it, as it is an infirmity to which our bodies are made ſubiect, and we muſt paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row it, as it is the way and gate into that glorious life in the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Thirdly, the Saints muſt die, that the diſcerning of the elect from the reprobate, may bee reſerued vnto the laſt day, the day of iudgement. According to the words of the Prophet <hi>Malachi;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>Then ſhall yee returne and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne betweene the righteous and the wicked, betweene him that ſerueth God, and him that ſerueth him not.</hi> Now if onely the reprobates, wicked men and hypocrites, did die, and the elect not die, then might it bee diſcerned who were elected and truly ſanctified, before that day come.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> Fourthly, that it may appeare no vaine word which God ſpake to <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaying;<note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eat thy bread till thou returne vnto the ground: for out of it waſt thou taken, for duſt thou art, and vnto duſt ſhalt thou returne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>5</label> Fiftly, that by taſting of bodily death, they may feele Gods mercy the ſweeter in freeing of them from death eternall, which they had likewiſe deſerued, and learne to ſet the more ſtore by the riches of his mercy, and accept it the better, and be prouoked to ſeeke it, and alſo receiue it, with the earneſter deſire and the greater thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. To that end are wee forced to paſſe thorow the death of the body. And indeed let vs conſider well the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6526:13"/>pride of our owne nature, the falſe ouerweening and vaine ſelfe-truſt wherewith we be puffed vp, how ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne we be againſt the Lord, and at how low a rate we priſe his goodneſſe, and wee ſhall finde, that to doe vs good and to bring vs to life, he muſt be faine to make vs paſſe thorow the gates of death. And why? To keepe vs in awe and humble vs, to make vs to know our ſelues, and how rich he is in mercy, in his dealing with vs; to the intent we may yeeld the more honour and reuerence to our onely wiſe, immortall and good God. And may ſay euery one of vs, alas, I might iuſtly haue beene ſunken before this day to the bottome of hell, and if God were not wondrous mercifull, what is due to my whole life for my manifold ſinnes? I haue deſerued to die not only the death of the body, but the ſecond death, euen the death of ſoule and body eternally. Thus you ſee how it is good for the Saints to be kept in awe, and taught humilitie, by being appointed to die.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>6</label> Sixtly, that they may be made partakers of the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reſurrection at the end of the world. For, to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a ſimilitude from the Apoſtles words:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.36.</note> as the corne which is ſowen is not quickened except it die: ſo is it with vs; wee cannot partake of the reſurrection of the iuſt, except we die. For they that remaine aliue at the comming of the Lord, ſhall not die to attaine vnto the reſurrection;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.51. 1 Theſſ. 4.15, 16, 17.</note> but they ſhall all bee changed, and bee hindmoſt in the company that ſhall meet the Lord in the aire.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>The Vſe.</hi> Firſt then, is it true? are the Saints ſubiect to death?<note place="margin">We muſt ponder vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, that we are ſubiect to death.</note> Let vs ponder vpon it, that we deſerue ſuch an vnhappy condition. And that were it not for Gods mercy vnto vs in Chriſt, contrary to that which we haue deſerued, we muſt all die and be damned for euermore. Let vs thinke vpon it. Neither let any thinke it ſtrange, becauſe Chriſt hath died for vs, and roſe againe, and are dead with Chriſt, and riſen againe with him, and when as our ſinnes are forgiuen and quite done away,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6526:13"/>which brought death vpon vs, that yet neuertheles God will not releaſe vs, but make vs drinke of deaths cup. For although we ought to be glad of it, becauſe God procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth &amp; dealeth in ſuch wiſe, that we be nothing hindred thereby, but that we may come boldly vnto the throne of grace, and call vpon him quietly and without diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and at the houre of death may commend our ſoules into his hands, and pray for the glorious reſurrection of our bodies, and (as it were) caſt our ſelues into his father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lap; although I ſay, we ought to be glad of this; yet is it good for vs to haue ſome feeling of the miſerie, into which we haue plunged our ſelues, not only to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vs, and that we ſhould ſet the more ſtore by his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as I ſaid before, but to make vs iudge our ſelues, that we be not iudged of the Lord, and to make vs by faith to lay the faſter hold vpon his gracious promiſes, and the more carefully to ſerue him with ſuch reuerence and feare, as is requiſite for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this conſideration that wee are ſubiect vnto death, ſhould rouze vs out of ſinne,<note place="margin">Awake from ſinne and leaue it.</note> and make vs ſhunne it, and hate the verie motions of it. For ſinne is the cauſe of all our miſerie and mortalitie. As the Prophet <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Lamentations; Wherefore doth man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.39.</note> 
               <hi>a man for the puniſhment of his ſinnes?</hi> Intimating that man by his ſinnes doth bring puniſhments vpon himſelfe. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Mac. Hom.</hi> 11. Iude 23. Mic. 3.1, 2. Amos 5.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>As by one man ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne: and ſo death paſſed vpon all men, for that all haue ſinned.</hi> Hee makes ſinne, ye ſee, the cauſe of all mens mortalitie. Wherefore ſhun ſinne, and as the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith; <hi>Hate euen the garment ſpotted by the fleſh.</hi> And be not like thoſe heads of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and Princes of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of whom <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> ſaith, that <hi>they hate the good, and loue the euill.</hi> Be not like to them; but as <hi>Amos</hi> ſaith: <hi>Seeke good, and not euill.</hi> And againe; <hi>Hate the euill, and loue the good.</hi> For ſay, wee muſt die, and cannot auoid it, whatſoeuer wee doe; yet take away ſinne, and the ſting of death is gone. For,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6526:14"/>as the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>The ſting of death is ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.56.</note> Let ſinne therefore be away, and death when it comes ſhall doe vs no hurt; nay, it ſhall be aduantage and gaine vnto vs, as the ſame Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>For to me to liue is Chriſt, and to die is gaine.</hi> This therefore ſhould rouze vs, and driue vs from ſinne. Tell mee, who but a mad man, would giue aduantage to his vtter enemie, whereby to ſpoile him? Now death is this enemie, and our ſinne is the adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. If we liue in ſinne, wee giue death the adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>age to, kill vs eternally: but if we coufeſſe and forſake our ſins, death hath no aduantage againſt vs, and come when it will, it ſhall doe vs no hurt. I beſeech you conſider of it, and turne from ſinne, from couetouſneſſe, pride, and from whatſoeuer God forbiddeth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, are the Saints ſubiect to death? Then are they after a ſort ſubiect to that which is the chiefeſt curſe that is fallen vpon mankinde.<note place="margin">Good and bad ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to death, and the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e afflictions: but with great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</note> For death is the chiefeſt curſe, and containeth vnder it all the curſes<note place="margin">n="a" Gen. 2.17.</note> that be fallen vpon mankinde. Howbeit this vnderſtand, that the Saints bee not ſubiect to death as it is a curſe, but as it is ſanctified, and become an entrance into life. And as they are ſubiect to death, ſo are they ſubiect likewiſe to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſeries that this life affords: to hunger, nakedneſſe, impriſonment, ſorrow, hatred, ſlanders, and manifold perſecutions and temptations. So that the Saints cannot bee diſcerned by their outward ſtate. But neuertheleſſe, betweene the ſame afflictions and manner of death fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon the Saints and vpon the vngodly there is great difference: becauſe the one are in Chriſt the fountaine of all goodneſſe and bleſſedneſſe, by whom all curſes are quite taken away; according to the words of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle;<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the curſe of the Law, being made a curſe for vs: for it is written, curſed is euerie one that hangeth on a tree.</hi> But the others, to wit, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, are our of Chriſt, and therefore vnder the curſe. Remember it then, that howſoeuer the ſame affliction and dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h may befall to the good and the bad, yet there is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6526:14"/>ſuch a change made by meanes of Chriſt, that they are farre vnlike vnto the one and the other. When <hi>Ioah</hi> had ſlaine <hi>Abner, Dauid</hi> lamenting ouer him, ſpake theſe words; <hi>Died Abner as a foole dieth?</hi> So wee may ſay,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.33.</note> Died <hi>Lazarus</hi> as the rich glutton died? or die the Saints as the vngodly doe die? yea, it is moſt certaine; as it happeneth to the vngodly, ſo it happeneth to the Saints: euen one thing befalleth them all: they all goe vnto one place, all are of the duſt, and all returne to duſt againe. But loe what followes; the Saints die to liue, but the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly die eternally. In the death of the Saints God is not their enemie, but in the death of the vngodly God is their enemie. The Saints death hath no ſting, but the death of the vngodly hath a moſt venomous ſting. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this difference, yet let the common condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good and bad bee carefully marked, to weane vs from the world, to make vs minde our home in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, and not to ſeeke our felicitie in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life. For here haue we no continuing citie, but wee ſeeke one to come. And there is no bodily miſerie,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.14.</note> euen vnto the death, that the vileſt miſcreants be ſubiect vnto, but the beſt that breathe are ſubiect to the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, can it not bee auoided, but that the Saints alſo muſt die? then muſt we prepare,<note place="margin">Prepare and be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ready for death. Certa ſtat omnibus mortis ſententia, hora autemnihil incertiuo.</note> and be alwayes in a readineſſe, that whenſoeuer death comes, it doe not take vs vnprouided. There is nothing more certaine, than that death will come: nor nothing more vncertaine, than at what time it will come. By experience we ſee it true: <hi>To day a man, to morrow none.</hi> It behoueth vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to bee prouided at all times. Wee ſee as young, as healthie, as ſtrong, as rich, as noble, and religious,<note place="margin">Aequa lege neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ſortitur ir ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; imos. Hor. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Mac. Hom. <hi>4. Iob 14.5.</hi>
               </note> as any of vs all, are taken away before our eyes. And we cannot alwayes liue here. Wee muſt goe the way that this our brother, and many thouſands more, haue gone before vs. And how ſoone, or whoſe turne may be the next, we doe not know. Our dayes are determined, the number of our moneths are with the Lord, hee hath appointed our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6526:15"/>bounds that we cannot paſſe. And hee that tarrieth lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt,<note place="margin">Iames 4.14.</note> ſhall not be long behinde. For what is our life? <hi>It is euen a vapour that appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away.</hi> Bee wee therefore ready to depart at all times when the Lord ſhall call vs.<note place="margin">Foure thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to be done to be alwayes ready for death.</note> And that we may bee alwayes ready; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt, let our houſes bee ſet in order, and euerie mans laſt will written, if hee meane to make any, that whenſoeuer the Lord ſhall call vs, nothing may trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vs that way. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, let vs bee continually doing the will of our heauenly Father. That whenſoeuer hee ſhall come,<note place="margin">Matth. 24.46.</note> he may finde vs ſo doing. <hi>Bleſſed is that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, whom his Lord when he commeth, ſhall finde ſo doing.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, by liuing in continuall expectance of death, not flattering our ſelues with a vaine hope of long life, like the rich man in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Luke 12.18, 9.</note> which built him greater barnes, perſwading himſelfe, that hee ſhould liue many yeeres about, at his owne eaſe and content: but making account that euerie day, nay euerie houre, may be our laſt houre, and the houre of our death. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, by furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing our ſelues with ſundry Chriſtian reſolutions and meditations;<note place="margin">Six godly meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt death.</note> as namely with theſe, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that it is better, and more acceptable to God, to offer that for a free will offering vnto God, I meane our ſoule and ſpirit, which otherwiſe we are bound to reſtore, as a thing that is due, and ſhall bee compelled to reſtore when the time is come, and doe what wee can.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.8.</note> For <hi>there is no man that hath power ouer the ſpirit to retaine the ſpirit, neither hath he power in the day of death: and there is no diſcharge in that warre, neither ſhall wickedneſſe deliuer them that are giuen to it.</hi> And indeed what win the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne fort, by their deſirouſneſſe of life, and loathneſſe to die, but this, to bee ouercome by force, when they haue ſtruggled and ſtriuen, as if they would ſight againſt God, and reſiſt his will?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, that as God hath ſet vs here, ſo he ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to haue the authority to take vs away againe when he liſteth himſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:6526:15"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, that euery child of God ought to be alwaies willing to goe whitherſoeuer God calleth him:<note place="margin">Cum accerſitionis propriae dies vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, incunctanter &amp; libenter ad Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ipſo vocante veniamus. Cyp. de Mortal. ſect. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> and whenſoeuer God giueth him any token that he will take him out of the world, it behooueth him alwaies to haue one foot onward in the way; as if he ſhould ſay, loe here I am, Lord, I am ready to anſwer thy call, and to come vnto thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, that this world is but a pilgrimage, and that we muſt hold on to paſſe apace thorow it, to come to our inheritance which is in heauen. This minde was in thoſe of the ancient Patriarkes of whom the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>they confeſſed that they were ſtrangers and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims on the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, that in as much as Chriſt Ieſus is our head, he will draw vs vp to himſelfe into the glory whereinto he himſelfe is entred already, that we may bee with him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.24.</note> where he is, to behold his glory which the Father hath giuen him: ſo we keepe faſt hold of him by a true and liuely faith, and be not ſeparated from him by grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weary of well doing, nor by embracing this preſent world, nor yet by continuance in ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, that the Saints of God which haue liued in times paſt, ſeeing their death to approach, haue not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted it nor beene diſmaied, but haue put themſelues into the hands of God, and haue prepared themſelues willingly to die. As <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.33.</note> when he had made an end of commanding his ſonnes, gathered vp his feet into the bed, and yeelded vp the ghoſt. And <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.48, 49, 50. &amp; 34.1, 7.</note> when God ſent him vp into the mountaine <hi>Abarim,</hi> vnto mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> and told him that he ſhould die there, repined not, but ſhewed all obedience, and prepared himſelfe vnto it, when hee ſaw it was Gods will that it ſhould bee ſo. And <hi>Pauls</hi> time drawing neere, he ſpeakes of himſelfe, as if when he were executed, he ſhould be offered vp in ſacrifice vnto God. <hi>For I am now ready to be offered,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>and the time of my departure is at hand.</hi> And before that, when <hi>Agabus</hi> the Prophet had ſhewed the danger that hee
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6526:16"/>ſhould be in, if he went vp to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and both they of his owne company, and the men of that place, that is of <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> had beſought him earneſtly not to goe vp, he was much troubled with their teares, and with the adoe which they made about him, but nothing at all with his owne afflictions and death. For he made them this anſwer,<note place="margin">Acts 21.13.</note> 
               <hi>What meane ye to weepe and to breake mine heart? For I am ready not to be bound only, but alſo to die at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem for the Name of the Lord Ieſus.</hi> I ſhould be long to ſpeake of <hi>Aaron,</hi> of <hi>Samuel,</hi> of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and of a great number of faithfull Martyrs. Yet I cannot omit the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt, which is the chiefeſt of all, who after he had drunke of the cup of his fathers wrath, the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt cup that euer man drunke of before his departure, commended his ſoule into his Fathers hands,<note place="margin">Luke 23.46.</note> and gaue vp the ghoſt. Theſe examples we muſt beare in minde, and ponder vpon them, to learne thereby, that whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer God ſhall call vs out of this world, we may not ſticke to goe willingly vnto him. On the one ſide is miſery, on the other a Crowne; on the one ſide a pilgrimage, on the other our ſaluation; and death is betweene. Shall we be afraid of death? There is no cauſe. For its ſting is gone, and when we haue paſſed thorow it, there ſhall be an end of our miſery, and we ſhall haue the crowne of righteouſneſſe: our pilgrimage ſhall ceaſe, and we ſhall receiue the end of our faith, the ſaluation of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Theſe meditations and reſolutions, and other ſuch like, being well digeſted and ſetled in our ſoules, will make vs euermore ready and well diſpoſed to depart out of this life, whenſoeuer God ſheweth vs that our houre is come.</p>
            <p>The death of his Saints.</p>
            <p>A Further thing that is worth the noting in theſe words of the text, <hi>The death of his Saints,</hi> is tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6526:16"/>the moſt happy eſtate of the children of God, in that they are called HIS <hi>Saints. The death of</hi> HIS <hi>Saints.</hi> Remember from hence, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Doct.</hi> The Saints are the Lords. And they are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lords as all men are, but after a peculiar manner.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Saints are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly the Lords.</hi> Deut. 32.9. 1 Pet. 2.9. Exod. 19.5.</note> They are the portion of the Lord, and the lot of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, a peculiar people, and to vſe <hi>Moſes</hi> words; they are <hi>a peculiar treaſure vnto him</hi> aboue all people: for all the earth is his. So that they may with much comfort thinke of the Apoſtles ſpeech:<note place="margin">Rom. 14.8.</note> 
               <hi>Whether we liue therefore or die, we are the Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſtion.<note place="margin">In ſix reſpects.</note> 
               <hi>How are they the Lords after a peculiar manner?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> In diuers reſpects. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in regard of their election. For as the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>He hath choſen vs in him,</hi> that is, in Chriſt as members in the head, <hi>before the foundation of the world, that we ſhould be holy and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blame before him in loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in regard of their calling: according to theſe words; <hi>vnto the Church of God which is at Corinth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Ieſus, called to be Saints.</hi> As many as are called, are not therefore called of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Saints: but therefore they are Saints, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are called of his grace. In this reſpect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Saints are the Lords.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, in regard of their iuſtification: becauſe the holineſſe of Chriſt is imputed vnto them to iuſtification, as I haue touched before,<note place="margin">Page 12.</note> by which they are made holy in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, in regard of their ſanctification, which for the beginning, continuance, encreaſe, and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, is wholly of God. As the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>And the very God of peace ſanctifie you wholly,</hi> that is, thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, in your whole ſoule and body.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, in regard of redemption: becauſe he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and deliuered vs out of the hands of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,<note place="margin">Luke 1.74, 75.</note> to ſerue him without feare, in holineſſe and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6526:17"/>before him all the daies of our life. To this effect ſaith <hi>Paul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>Ye are bought with a price.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, in regard of their owne deuoting and addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of themſelues to doe his will.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.38.</note> As <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith; <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh thy word vnto thy ſeruant: who is deuoted to thy feare.</hi> And this the Saints doe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acti agimu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Cant. 1.4.</note> not of themſelues, but through the grace of the Spirit, which firſt moueth and ſtirreth them. For the ability to moue to any thing pleaſing to God, is meerely from his grace.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Firſt, ye ſee then, if we be of the number of the Saints,<note place="margin">Yee Saints, ſtudy to pleaſe the Lord, and ſerue him.</note> that is to ſay, of Gods faithfull ſeruants, how many waies God hath a peculiar title vnto vs; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in how many reſpects we are peculiarly obliged aboue all the men of the world, vnto the Lord: to wit, in reſpect of our election, vocation, iuſtification, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, redemption, and the willing addicting of our ſelues through his grace vnto his ſeruice. What remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth then, but that we ſtudy in all things to pleaſe the Lord, and obey his Commandements? As the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">Col. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>That ye might walke worthy of the Lord vnto all pleaſing, being fruitfull in euery good worke, and increaſing in the knowledge of God.</hi> The Apoſtle, yee ſee, would haue vs <hi>walke worthy of the Lord,</hi> that is, that our life ſhould be proportionable to the meaſure of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God towards vs. We hauing therefore receiued ſo great mercy of the Lord ſo many waies, we muſt leade our liues in a proportionable meaſure of holineſſe and obedience. We muſt not breake out into blaſphemous oathes, curſed ſpeaking, drunkenneſſe, riot, ſtealing, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and other filthineſſe of life, as many doe; but thinking how good the Lord is, and hath beene vnto vs, wee muſt walke worthy of his Mercy. Hath hee taken vs to himſelfe after a peculiar manner? Hath he made vs ſome of his Saints? He hath not dealt ſo with a great number of people which were as good as our ſelues, nay farre before vs in many reſpects. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt worſhip him better than they doe, and
<pb facs="tcp:6526:17"/>yeeld him that honour which a great number will not yeeld him. Where others will not ſtoupe, there we muſt ſtoupe: and his doctrine which they refuſe and will not receiue, we muſt receiue it with meekeneſſe, and be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient thereunto. For as the earth rendereth to the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman the fruit of his paines beſtowed vpon it: ſo we muſt render to the Lord the fruit of his manifold mercies beſtowed vpon vs, and that is repentance, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of all vngodlineſſe, and a liuing ſoberly, and righteouſly and godly in this preſent world.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it being ſo that the Saints be the Lords af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo peculiar a manner,<note place="margin">Affect the Saints company, and to be of their number. <hi>Pſal. 16.2, 3. and 119.63.</hi> See alſo <hi>Pſ. 101.6.</hi>
               </note> it ſhould moue vs to affect the company of the Saints. As <hi>Dauid</hi> did, ſaying; <hi>My good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe extendeth not to thee: But to the Saints, that are in the earth, and to the excellent, in whom is all my delight.</hi> And againe; <hi>I am a companion of all them that feare thee: and of them that keepe thy precepts.</hi> And as we deſire the company of the Saints,<note place="margin">Pro. 1.15. and 23.20. 1 Cor. 5.9, 10, 11. 2 Theſſ. 3.14.</note> ſo ſhould we loath and eſchew the ſociety of Atheiſts, drunkards, fornicators, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and all wicked and vngodly perſons. Neither is it enough to affect the Saints company, but we muſt ſtriue and labour to be ſome of their number. <hi>Iudas</hi> the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor got little in the ſight of God by conuerſing with Chriſt and his holy Apoſtles, being himſelfe a deuill. And ſo it ſhall little auaile vs to be continually with the Saints, if we be not our ſelues ſome of the number of the Saints.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.40, 41. Luk. 17.34, 35, 36.</note> For when the Lord ſhall come, the Saints ſhall be taken, and we ſhall be left.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, this conſidered, that the Saints be the Lords, and that after ſo peculiar a manner as no men elſe,<note place="margin">No reprobate can be truly ſanctified.</note> it muſt needs follow, that neuer a reprobate can be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. They may make a ſhew and profeſſion of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but the truth and rooted ſoundneſſe thereof, they can neuer haue. No? cannot a reprobate be ſanctified? Doth not <hi>Paul</hi> make mention of ſome, <hi>that they counted the bloud of the couenant wherewith they were ſanctified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:6526:18"/>Yet were they ſanctified. True. But how were they ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified? <hi>By the bloud of the Couenant,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; that is, not by the effectuall and gracious working of the Spirit creating in them, as in the elect, conuerted ſoules, that new quality of holineſſe, whereby they can in ſome meaſure truly hate their owne ſinnes, with a firme pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to leaue them; and can loue Gods law, with a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to performe it in ſome good meaſure: not ſo; but ſacramentally only. And ſo many a reprobate may bee ſanctified, that is to ſay, he may be baptiſed. Nay more, he may be outwardly reformed, and haue ſome inward good things, as ioy in hearing of the word, and he may be ſanctified in the charitable opinion of others, yea and in his owne conceit and perſwaſion; and yet all the while want that peculiar worke of the ſpirit of God, of which I ſpake euen now, and ſo be deſtitute of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and truth of the grace of ſanctification. For this he can neuer haue, make what ſhew he will: It is the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods elect: it is part of his childrens bread; he will not take it and caſt it vnto dogs. It is a holy thing, not fit for dogs, and a pearle of more worth than to be caſt before ſwine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, conſidering that the Saints be the Lords after a peculiar manner,<note place="margin">It is a ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to be truly ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.</note> what a comfort is it to bee truly ſanctified? He that is ſuch a one may build vpon it, that God will protect him, and that he ſhall be ſaued. For as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Pro. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>He preſerueth the way of his Saints.</hi> And <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Iude 1.</note> 
               <hi>to them that are ſanctified by God the Father, and preſerued in Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> to wit, to life eternall, <hi>and called.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 33.3.</note> And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith; <hi>All his Saints are in thy hand.</hi> Which is more for their ſafety, than if they had all the caſtles and bulwarks of the world to defend and ſaue them. For we know what Chriſt ſaith: <hi>No man is able to plucke them out of my Fathers hand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 10.29.</note> So that it is a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous comfort to be truly ſanctified. Such may haue enemies both many, and mighty, by whom they may looke to be fiercely aſſaulted, but no multitudes nor
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6526:18"/>power can preuaile againſt them. And albeit they ſeeme often to be ouerthrowne with the wrongs which they ſuffer, as ſome are ſtript of their poſſeſſions, others are impriſoned, others are baniſhed, others are tormented, others are killed; yet they are ſtill the Lords. And this that they are ſo dealt with, commeth not to paſſe through the might of their aduerſaries, but by the will of God; neither doth he ſuffer it to ſatisfie their foes, but to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their owne happineſſe.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>For our light affliction which is but for a moment, worketh for vs a farre more exceeding and eternall waight of glory.</hi> And beſides, in all their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions he careth for them, and doth them good.</p>
            <p>Queſtion.<note place="margin">Six markes of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification.</note> 
               <hi>But how ſhall I know that I am truly ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, by a perfect, that is to ſay, a ſincere and true hatred of euery ſinne, whatſoeuer gaine or pleaſure it may ſeeme to bring with it, and by the practiſe of all holy duties, though our credit, peace, wealth, and all that we haue muſt goe to wracke for it, yea &amp; our life it ſelfe be endangered thereby. For a man truly ſanctified will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe life and all, rather than obedience to Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. <hi>How can I doe this great wickedneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39.9.</note> 
               <hi>and ſinne againſt God?</hi> ſaid <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, by the ground of our hatred of ſinne, and practiſe of vertue, if it be not our owne credit amongſt good men, nor any other by-reſpects, but the will and Commandement of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, by the right end propoſed, we hating ſinne, euen in the ſecreteſt cloſet of our ſoule, and purging it from the fleſh and ſpirit; and perfecting holineſſe in the feare of God, that now and alwaies Chriſt may be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified and God be glorified in vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, by the meanes by which ſanctification was wrought. That is to ſay, if we haue attained to ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by the effectuall working of the Spirit, and the doctrine of the word. For theſe bee the meanes, by which God doth ſanctifie vs. And for this, ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6526:19"/>is called,<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.13. Iohn 17.17.</note> 
               <hi>the ſanctification of the Spirit.</hi> And our Sauiour ſaith; <hi>Sanctifie them through thy truth: thy word is truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, by the extent of it. For true ſanctification ſpreads ouer the whole man;<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.23.</note> it is wrought in the whole ſpirit and ſoule and body.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, by the continuance and growth of it. For true ſanctification after it is once wrought, continues for euer, and growes more and more by the ſelfe-ſame meanes by which it was firſt wrought, vntill it come to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>The death of his Saints.</p>
            <p>LAſtly from theſe words, in that the deare children of God, whoſe dignity is great, and farre beyond the higheſt dignitie, that this world affoords; in that theſe are expreſſed vnder this title of <hi>Saints,</hi> I gather, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Doct.</hi> The very title of a Saint is full of honour and dignity.<note place="margin">The title of a Saint is honourable.</note> The Scripture, yee ſee, when it makes menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the beſt, and of ſuch as the world is not worthy of, expreſſeth them here, and many times elſewhere, by the title of Saints.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 6.41.</note> 
               <hi>Let thy Saints reioyce in goodneſſe,</hi> ſaid <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> in his praier.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>The Vſe.</hi> Firſt the hearing of this muſt teach the Saints to walke in holineſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Walke in holineſſe.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.15, 16.</note> According to <hi>S. Peters</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation: <hi>But as he which hath called you is holy, ſo bee ye holy in all mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of conuerſation. Becauſe it is written, Be ye holy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>for I am holy.</hi> And <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith thus; <hi>walke in loue, as Chriſt alſo hath loued vs, and hath giuen himſelfe for vs, an offering and a ſacrifice to God for a ſweet ſmelling ſauour: But fornication and all vncleanneſſe, or couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, let it not bee once named among you, as becommeth Saints.</hi> Here is the ground of his exhortation, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued ſo great mercy and grace as to bee made Saints, wee are to walke as is fitting for the Saints of God. And it ſhould bee a ſhame that any profeſſing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6526:19"/>themſelues Saints, ſhould be found vnholy in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, conſidering this, is it not a ſtrange thing, that any liuing in the Church,<note place="margin">Againſt them that reproach others with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and make a mocke at the title of a Saint.</note> hearing the Goſpell, and knowing their Creed, ſhould be ſo ſtrangely blinded, and ſo deſperately wicked, as to ſcoffe at the endeuour and practiſe of ſanctitie, and reproach others with their holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſaying, <hi>You are one of theſe holy folke;</hi> nay, ſo graceleſſe and ignorant as to turne this very title into matter of reproach, ſaying; <hi>You are one of the Saints, you know your place in heauen already.</hi> But doeſt thou know thy ſelfe? Canſt thou tell me what thou art thy ſelfe, thou that after this faſhion doeſt make a ſcorne of other mens holineſſe, and of the bleſſed title of a Saint? I muſt tell thee plainly, that both thou and all others that make a ſcoffe at holineſſe, and that ſcorne the title of a Saint, yee are none of Gods children, yee are vnholy Atheiſts, and very Deuils incarnate. Conſider well of it, and pray God to enlighten you, and turned our hearts.</p>
            <p>And as for the children of God,<note place="margin">Foure comforts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reproaches for holineſſe.</note> they haue many good meditations to comfort themſelues with againſt theſe kinde of reproches: and namely theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that it is a great honour to bee of the number of the Lords Saints. And if the vngodly will turne their glorie in to ſhame, yet as they deſire not to haue the Sonne of man to be aſhamed of them when bee commeth in the glorie of his Father, with the holy angels, ſo muſt they not be aſhamed to profeſſe themſelues, his Saints, which is their glorie. They muſt ſuffer none, neither by repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, nor any other way, to take this crowne from them. For the ſtate of a Saint is not ſuch a ſtate, that they need to be aſhamed of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, that the Lord calleth them to be his Saints, and maketh his promiſe with them to preſerue and keepe them. And faithfull is hee that calleth them,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.24.</note> who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo will doe it. Hee will neuer leaue them, nor forſake them.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:6526:20"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, that all the malice which men doe beare them, and the ſcoffes that they are reproached with, are occaſioned by their holineſſe, which is Gods gracious gift vnto them. Their holineſſe is the cauſe which enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the vngodly.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.4.</note> As <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith: <hi>Againe, I conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all trauell, and euery right worke, that for this a man is enuied of his neighbour: this alſo is vanitie, and vexation of ſpirit.</hi> But God will ariſe and maintaine his owne cauſe, and auenge all their wrongs,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.7. &amp;c.</note> no otherwiſe than <hi>Dauid</hi> did the indignities of his ſeruants vpon <hi>Hanun</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nahaſh,</hi> the King of the children of <hi>Ammon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, that when vngodly men doe ſtout them with their ſanctitie and holineſſe, that they are neere and dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vnto the Lord. For they are his friends, they are his people, they are his ſeruants, his children, his ſpouſe, yea, as the tendereſt members of his body vnto him. For as ſaith the Prophet <hi>Zechariah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of his eye.</hi> And ſo long as the Lord doth acknowledge them for ſome of his, and doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them ſo neere and deare vnto himſelfe, they need not greatly cure for any reproaches of men. For his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour is enough to counteruaile all. So that as <hi>Elkanah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hannah,</hi> comforting her againſt her barrenneſſe; <hi>Am not I better to thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>than ten ſonnes?</hi> So may euerie one of vs ſay, of the fauour of God, when all men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach vs, and none care for vs; Is not the fauour of God better to vs, than all the kindneſſe and fauour of the men of this world? And thus may wee comfort our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all manner of reproaches for holineſſe ſake.</p>
            <p>Thus farre of the ſubiect of the propoſition. Now the <hi>Conſequent</hi> followeth, in theſe words; <hi>is precious.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:20"/>
            <p> Precious is the death of his Saints. <hi>Or more plainly:</hi> The death of his Saints is precious.</p>
            <p>WHat meanes this; <hi>The death of his Saints is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous?</hi> For this may ſeeme a Paradox, and beyond the credit of all men, that the death or any ſhould come to be precious, ſeeing death came by ſinne, and is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon looking-glaſſe, and record vnto vs of Gods curſe, not vpon one or two folkes, but vpon all mankinde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The meaning is, that the death of the Saints is of great eſteeme and honourable in Gods account, and very profitable for themſelues. But not in it ſelfe, but by accident only: that which in it ſelfe is the wages of ſinne and a curſe, being by the grace of God and the death of Chriſt turned cleane about, and made an excellent bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Remember it then, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>Doct.</hi> The death of the Saints is a matter of great price. It is much ſet by in the ſight of the Lord:<note place="margin">The Saints death is precious. Mors Sanctorum eſt finis &amp; meta laborum, conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio victoriae, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rina vitae, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectae eternaeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecuritatis ingreſſio. Bern.</note> and in regard of themſelues it is truly precious, as being the end of their labours, the conſumination of their victorie, the gate of life, and an entrance into moſt perfect ſecuritie.</p>
            <p>Wee haue a world of meditations to cleare the truth of this. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> For firſt the Lord affirmes it, who is truth it ſelfe, and cannot lie, that <hi>precious is the death of his Saints.</hi> And how can it bee otherwiſe, ſeeing <hi>they die vnto the Lord,</hi> and <hi>ſleepe in Ieſus,</hi> as the Scripture ſpeakes?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.8. 1 Theſſ. 4.14, 16.</note> by death they are more neerely vnited to their ſoueraigne and chiefeſt good, euen to God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For the further off that any is from ſinne, ſo much the neerer he is ioyned to God, that pure, and perpetuall, and immortall good, to cleaue faſt vnto him, and to bee alwayes with him, whoſe of-ſpring he is; as the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>For we are alſo his of-ſpring.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17.28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Thirdly, becauſe by death they are gathered to the ancient Patriarkes, to the holy Prophets, and Apoſtles,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6526:21"/>to the aſſembly of the Saints, to their owne deare pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, children, brethren, ſiſters, kinsfolke, and friends, which are gone to heauen before them: and which is more than all this, to Ieſus Chriſt their Redeemer, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe of their heauenly Father, in which he hath prepared a placefor vs;<note place="margin">Heb. 6.20. and 10.20.</note> into heauen whither the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner is for vs entred, euen Ieſus Chriſt: by a new and liuing way which he hath conſecrated for vs through the vaile, that is to ſay, his fleſh. And whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he is gone before, that we might follow him, whenſoeuer he ſhall pleaſe to call vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> Fourthly, becauſe it puts an end to all the cares, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, teares and miſeries, to which all are ſubiect in this life. For this cauſe death is preferred before life, and the condition of the dead, before the condition of the liuing,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.1, 2.</note> in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> where <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith; <hi>So I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and conſidered all the oppreſſions that are done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sunne; and behold the teares of ſuch as were op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and they had no comforter; and on the ſide of their oppreſſors there was power, but they had no comforter. Wherefore I praiſed the dead which are already dead, more than the liuing which are yet aliue.</hi> Death takes vs away from their enuie that now liue, and ſets vs free from all feare of them, which are yet to come.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>5</label> Fiftly, becauſe it looſeth the Saints from the bonds of temptations, and the ſnares of ſinne, and ſendeth them into true libertie. As long as the ſoule continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the body, the bonds of temptations hang as fetters about it, and bring it into captiuitie to the law of ſinne, neither can it get free from theſe bonds and ſhackles: but when it departeth from the body, it is looſed from the bonds of temptations, and goeth into a bleſſed and heauenly freedome. To this effect ſaith <hi>Paul;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>He that is dead, is freed from ſinne.</hi> After death the temptations ceaſe, which all the life time did tye the ſoule, and leade it into captiuitie to the law of ſinne. So that now there is no ſuch tying, nor leading captiue
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6526:21"/>of the Saints, but an enioying of perfect freedome for euermore.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>6</label> Sixthly, becauſe it taketh away the Saints out of this preſent euill world; in which if they haue outward peace, (which is alſo ſickle and vncertaine) yet they ſhall be ſure to haue bodily paine and vexation of ſpirit. For that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence cannot be reuoked;<note place="margin">Iob 14.22.</note> 
               <hi>But his fleſh vpon him ſhall haue paine, and his ſoule within him ſhall mourne.</hi> This is the lot of the liuing; neither can we be freed from it vntill death come. And a thouſand things there be to diſquiet and grieue our mindes, but nothing more than the riſeneſſe of ſinne. For as the filthy conuerſation of the wicked <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> vexed <hi>Lot;</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> witneſſeth, ſaying;<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>That righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man dwelling among them, in ſeeing and hearing vexed his righteous ſoule from day to day with their vnlawfull deedes:</hi> So the Saints at this day cannot chooſe but be vexed in ſeeing and hearing ſo many enormous vices to be daily committed. Such renting of God in peeces by fearefull oathes, ſuch curſing and lying, ſuch exceſſiue drinking and drunkenneſſe, ſuch breaking of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, ſuch deuices and ſlanders to diſgrace Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and to hinder the free paſſage of the Goſpell, with a thouſand enormities more, make euery Chriſtian heart ake, and fill it full of vexation from day to day. From this alſo death frees vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>7</label> Seuenthly, becauſe it puts an end to the moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous combat in the world, which we are forced to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure as long as we liue here, and in which we muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffer blowes, I meane, the buffetings of Satan, or elſe fall, one of the two. What doe we alwaies in this life, but fight continually againſt principalities, againſt powers, againſt the rulers of the darkneſſe of this world, againſt Spirituall wickedneſſe in high places? Beſides, we haue combating with couetouſneſſe, with inordinate luſts, with angrineſſe, with vaineglory. Our minde is encloſed and beſet round about with the aſſaults of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and with manifold temptations: and theſe come ſo
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6526:22"/>thicke one vpon the necke of another, that it can ſcarce meet with euery one of them; and them that it doth meet with, it is hard to reſiſt almoſt any one of them. If couetouſneſſe be ſubdued, luſt ariſeth; if luſt be maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, vaineglory ſtirres; if vaineglory be vanquiſhed, angrineſſe comes in place; pride ſwelleth, enuie vrgeth, and heat of ſpirit breakes forth and makes diſcord. The world alſo, and our owne fleſh make many aſſaults vpon vs, and much annoy vs. Of all this and a great deale more doth death make an end.</p>
            <p>And what ſhall I ſay more? For the time would faile me to produce all the meditations that make for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And that which hath beene ſaid doth abundantly proue, that the death of the Saints, as the Pſalmiſt here ſaith, <hi>is precious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obiection.<note place="margin">It by the preciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Saints death is not viſible.</note> 
               <hi>But ſome may thinke that all this is but words, and that he ſees no ſuch matter in the death of the Saints, but that they die as other men doe; If their death be ſo precious, why doth it not appeare ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Their death is precious, but yet it doth not appeare ſo; firſt, becauſe it is no treaſure of this world, but an heauenly treaſure. I ſay, the preciouſneſſe of the Saints death is an heauenly treaſure, and therefore hid from the ſight of carnal eies in that treaſurie of the Lords, in Ieſus Chriſt, by whoſe death it is made precious.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, notwithſtanding it appeare not, yet we haue a moſt ſure word for it, euen the word of the Lord that cannot lie, witneſſing that it is ſo. And that is better for vs than if it did appeare. For our eies might deceiue vs, as theirs that tooke Chriſt for a ſpirit, and our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are dimme and not able to iudge in ſuch matters, but Gods word cannot deceiue vs, but put vs out of doubt in the matter.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the time is not yet come that it muſt appeare: but it will come, and then it ſhall be manifeſt to the whole world, that it hath beene ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, though it appeare not to mortall eyes, yet
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6526:22"/>we ſee it by faith. Our eies are no iudges in this caſe, and the world is worſe than our eies. For the glory is not earthly, nor knowne to the men of this world, whereof we ſpeake, but the treaſure is ſpirituall, and of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall man it is diſcerned. Know thy ſelfe, that by faith thou art Chriſts, and he thine, that he died for thee, and thou liueſt by him, that thou art a member of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones, and whatſoeuer is his, is thine: haue this faith, and now come and ſee, and thou ſhalt ſee all the rubies, and precious things in the world, leſſe precious than the death of ſuch a man as thou art. Thy faith if it could comprehend more aſſurance of the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the Sunne, yet ſhouldeſt thou ſee the preciouſneſſe of it, aboue all thy thoughts. For who can comprehend how precious that is, which is prcious in Gods ſight?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Firſt, we behold in this the great goodneſſe of God,<note place="margin">See Gods goodneſſe in changing euill to good, to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. <hi>Rom. 8.28.</hi>
               </note> who changeth euill into good vnto his faithfull ſeruants; that it may be euery way, and for euer true, which the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>We know that all things worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for good, to them that loue God, to them who are the called according to his purpoſe.</hi> All things in generall, euen thoſe that ſeeme moſt to hinder our felicitie, are made of God to ſerue as helpes and furtherances thereof. When it commeth to death, in which is ſome token of Gods wrath, death is turned to our gaine and profit, ſo that we haue cauſe to reioice in all reſpects; and to hearken to the Apoſtle, when he ſaith; <hi>All things are yours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>whether Paul, or Apollo, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things preſent, or things to come, all are yours:</hi> that is, all are for your good.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, by that which hath beene ſaid it is alſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that there is a great difference betweene the bodily death of the godly, &amp; of the vngodly.<note place="margin">There is great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene the death of the godly and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</note> This appeares many waies. For the godly die in the Lord; the vngodly die in their ſins. The godly haue their death turned into a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: the death of the vngodly remaineth ſtil a curſe. To the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6526:23"/>godly to die is gaine:<note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note> to the vngodly to die is loſſe; for they loſe the comforts which now they enioy, &amp; the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, which they hoped for. The death of the godly is a paſſage into life:<note place="margin">Iohn 5.24.</note> the death of the vngodly is a paſſage to damnation. The godly being dead doe liue to God:<note place="margin">Luke 16.22, 23.</note> the vngodly doe die eternally. The ſoules of the godly when they depart from the body, be carried by the Angels into heauen: the ſoules of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly goe to torment in hell.<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.2.</note> The death of the godly is the end of their miſery; for when they die, they enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peace and reſt: the death of the vngodly is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their torment, and euerlaſting paine. The death of the godly is precious:<note place="margin">Mors peccatorum mala, pejor, peſſima: ſed bonorum mors bona, melior, opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Mors ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti eſt bona propter requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m: melior propter nouitatem: optima propter ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitatem. Idem.</note> the death of the vngodly is moſt vile and ſhamefull. To be ſhort, <hi>the death of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>is bad, worſer, worſt of all, but the death of the godly is good, better, beſt of all. Good, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the reſt that it bringeth with it: Better, becauſe it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth vs; Beſt of all, becauſe it putteth vs out of danger, and ſecureth vs for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, conſidering the preciouſneſſe of the death of the Saints, let euery man boaſt himſelfe as he will, ſome of their Parents and noble progenitors,<note place="margin">Reioice in this, that thou art a Saint.</note> ſome of riches, ſome of horſes, ſome of one thing, ſome of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and let the prophane of the world make a ſcoffe at holineſſe, and abhorre to the death the very name of a Saint, and let them hinder the meanes of holineſſe, as much as they can, ſpeaking euill of the waies of the Lord; this let others doe. Yet thou, if thou wilt attaine vnto ſuch a death as is precious in Gods ſight, which onely is comfortable, and a paſſage into life, doe thou: boaſt thy ſelfe of a ſanctified heart; yea glory of this, that thou art a Saint; and further the meanes of holineſſe to the vtmoſt of thy power, as the faithfull preaching of the word, the priuate reading of the Scriptures, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating and conferring of Sermons, and the like.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, conſidering as the Pſalmiſt ſaith that the Saints death is precious,<note place="margin">Judge aright of the Saints.</note> wee learne to bee of another
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6526:23"/>iudgement than the world is of concerning the Saints vpon earth. The Saints zeale in religion, and integrity of life is oftentimes ſuch, that it cauſeth men to neglect them, yea to maligne them, yea to cry our vpon them; peraduenture alſo to perſecute, impriſon, and put them to death: And when the world ſees this, they thinke them forlorne and miſerable creatures. But loe, their death is precious, and happineſſe is treaſured vp in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for them. Therefore wee ſhould count them happy, and be of the minde to adioyne our ſelues to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and become like them which are ſo little regarded, and ſo hardly thought of for their holineſſe ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label> Fiftly, this alſo is for the comfort of the Saints of God againſt the perſecutions of vngodly men.<note place="margin">Comfort againſt cruell perſecutions.</note> Let all the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly band themſelues, and lift vp their hands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, what can they doe? They cannot deuiſe the meanes to doe thee any finall hurt.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> All things ſhall worke together for the beſt to thee that loueſt God. It is not poſſible for man to alter this. Looke vpon thy death, that is precious and gainefull. They can doe nothing vnto thee, but that which in the end ſhall make for thy good. Looke further alſo throughout the bounds and compaſſe of the whole heauen and earth, and with pure eies, euen with the eies of faith thou ſeeſt excellent things; thou ſeeſt the firſt ſorrow caſt out with ſhame, death trodden vnder feet, hell aboliſhed, the Angels encamping about thee, Saints and Angels before thee, a bleſſed immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality lengthening thy daies, and the glory of God is before thine eies,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18</note> and with open face thou beholdeſt it as in a glaſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>6</label> Sixtly, heere is comfort for the Saints againſt the feare of death approaching. Build vpon this,<note place="margin">Comfort againſt the feare of death.</note> if thou beeſt a Saint, thy death ſhall be precious. There is no euill in it that thou needeſt to feare. And although thou muſt of neceſſity paſſe that way, with all other creatures, (for it is the way of all the earth:) yet doth God take thee and keepe thee, as his choſen child. And if thou belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6526:24"/>that Ieſus died and roſe againe:<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.14.</note> ſo aſſure thy ſelfe, that thee alſo, and all them which ſleepe in Ieſus will God bring with him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>7</label> Seuenthly, to conclude; this point is a good ground of comfort to the friends of the dead.<note place="margin">Comfort to the friends of him that died a Saint.</note> Died he a Saint? nay liued he a Saint? for if he liued a Saint, there is no queſtion of his death, but he died a Saint. For hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not die euilly,<note place="margin">Non poteſt malè mori, qui bene vix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crit. Auguſt.</note> who hath liued well. The diſeaſe may be ſuch, that either the ſpeech may be hindered, or elſe idle, and accompanied with ſome vnſeemely motions and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, which none muſt be diſmaied at, but take in good part euen in this regard,<note place="margin">Cuivis quod cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam.</note> becauſe we our ſelues may be in the like caſe. I ſay not therefore, died hee a Saint? but that euery ones comfort may be the fuller; liued hee a Saint? For we muſt not thinke ſo much of the manner of the death,<note place="margin">Non mola mors pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanda eſt, quam bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na vita praeceſſerit. Auguſt.</note> as of the tenour of the life. Neither muſt we thinke that death to bee euill, before which there hath gone an holy life. So then heere is the comfort. Hath he liued a Saint, and is he dead? He is bleſſed in heauen. Why mourne ye? weepe not for him, his death is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. Weepe for your ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Foure comforts for them that mourne ouer the dead.</note>And yet weepe not exceſſiuely, but remember; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> that God gaue him you but for a while, and therefore ye muſt not take it grieuouſly if he hath called him againe from you. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> that he ſhall in a glorified body be reſtored vnto you, and ioyned with you in the next life. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that it goeth well with him that is deliuered from ſo many perils and miſchiefes, as the Lord hath foretold ſhould fall out in this laſt age. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> that he is well prouided for before the Lord, and in farre better caſe than we that be aliue.</p>
            <p>Precious is the death of his Saints.</p>
            <p>Moreouer from this that the Saints death is here ſaid, &amp; ſo expreſly affirmed to be precious in the ſight of the Lord, I gather this comfortable meditation; that</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:6526:24"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>Doct.</hi> The Saints are neuer neglected of their louing God, neither doth death befall them without his ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prouidence.<note place="margin">God regards his Saints both in life and death.</note> If in their life time they meet with cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, ſo that they mourne, hee regards their teares: which made <hi>Dauid</hi> pray ſaying:<note place="margin">Pſal. 56.8.</note> 
               <hi>Put thou my teares into thy bottle.</hi> And at their death he looketh after them. Yea both in life and death he hath a gracious reſpect of them. His Angell in their life time encampeth round about them: and when they die, they are caried by the Angels,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.7.</note> as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was, into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, that is to ſay,<note place="margin">Luke 16.22.</note> into the place of bliſſe, where <hi>Abraham</hi> now is, with the reſt of Gods elect which be departed this life. This care hath God of euery one of his Saints. So that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can befall them in life or death, but as he diſpoſeth it. What time he will haue them to liue, ſo long they ſhall liue; as he will haue them to bee tried with ſundry afflictions, ſo are they euery one tried; and when his time is come, that he will haue them to die, then and not before, they ſhall depart this life. And (which is moſt comfortable) when that day comes, hee will draw neere vnto them, and make them feele by experience that which they haue learned, and beleeued long before, that <hi>precious in his ſight is the death of his Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Now then beloued, ſee what a gracious God the Saints haue in heauen. It is moſt true,<note place="margin">Take notice of Gods goodneſſe to his Saints.</note> and too too commonly ſeene, that generally amongſt men, the Saints of all others are leaſt regarded: but with the Lord of heauen there is none regarded with any ſpeciall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, but onely the Saints: and theſe hee reſpects after a ſpeciall manner; as the Pſalmiſt faith: <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 33.18. &amp; 34.15.</note> 
               <hi>the eye of the Lord is vpon them that feare him: vpon them that hope in his mercie.</hi> Many parents are very carefull for the welfare of their children: but no parents care can be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the care which God hath of his Saints. For notwithſtanding the greateſt care of the beſt parents in the world, yet ſome things they ſhall ſee to befall their children, which they cannot doe to, and which they
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6526:25"/>were not able for their liues to preuent: but in reſpect of the Lord, there is no ſuch thing can befall his Saints: but whatſoeuer he pleaſeth, and whatſoeuer his hand and his counſell hath determined before to be done, that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall befall them, both in life and death.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this ſerues to baniſh from the heart of euery good man,<note place="margin">To baniſh diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> all diſtracting thoughts, whether concerning maintenance, bodily ſafety, protection from dangers, or whatſoeuer thing elſe, and to make vs cheere vp our ſelues, &amp; learne that good leſſon which <hi>Dauid</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.22.</note> ſaying; <hi>Caſt thy burden vpon the Lord, and he ſhall ſuſtaine thee: he ſhall neuer ſuffer the righteous to be moued.</hi> Behold and know, that the Lord careth for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and ſendeth foorth his holy Angels, which are all miniſtring ſpirits,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.14. Pſ. 42.11. &amp; 43.5.</note> to miniſter for them, who ſhall be heires of ſaluation. Doſt thou beleeue this? then let not thy ſoule be diſquieted within thee, but hope in God: Be doing good, and fulfill thy duty in that place which God hath ſet thee. He will ſurely bleſſe thee, and keepe no good thing from thee, and at the laſt thy death ſhall be precious. For God himſelfe will haue the whole ordering of it, both for the time, the manner, the place, and euery way elſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, this alſo is comfortable for them that mourne for the death of any that liued in the feare of God.<note place="margin">Comfort ouer the Saints death.</note> Conſider this ſpeech well: <hi>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi> For this beeing true, that the Saints death is precious in the ſight of the Lord, it muſt needs follow, that whenſoeuer they die, bee it ſooner or latter, they die in the due time, that is to ſay, in that time which is beſt for them in reſpect of their good. It is the portion of bloudy and deceitfull men not to liue out halfe their daies:<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.23. Iob 5.26.</note> but it is otherwiſe with good men, as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaith; <hi>Thou ſhalt come to thy graue in a full age, like as a ſhocke of corne commeth in, in his ſeaſon.</hi> Oh then, thinke, when thy Chriſtian friend is taken from thee, that he died not by chance, he died not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6526:25"/>his time: but his time was come and God hath 1296 ſent him to his graue in his ſeaſon, yea euen in that time, when it was beſt for him, and moſt for the comfort and ſaluation of his ſoule. What couldeſt thou deſire more? Therefore mourne not exceſſiuely, but comfort thy ſelfe, and make ready for the time which God hath appointed for thee. It will not be long ere thou ſhalt goe the way, which thy louing friend, thy guide and thy comfort, is gone before thee. For death is the way of all the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, this meditation that the Saints are neuer neglected, neither in life nor death, of their louing God,<note place="margin">Encour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gement to ſerue God and truſt 1 in him.</note> ſhould both embolden vs, (come what will come) to goe on in his ſeruice, not being diſmaied with any croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or afflictions; and alſo make vs to truſt ſtedfaſtly in him, yea euen then, when we can diſcerne no tokens of his fauour vnto vs. For of this wee are certaine, that if we walke in holineſſe, howſoeuer it bee with vs all our life long, that God watcheth ouer vs, and our death when it comes, ſhall be precious in his ſight. And this we haue further for our comfort in this caſe, that we ſhall not die, when the vngodly would haue vs die, but at that time which God hath ſet. For as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, ſo we may euery one ſay, <hi>My times are in thy hand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 31.15. and 41.5.</note> The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly may ſay by vs, as they did by him; <hi>when ſhall hee die, and his name periſh?</hi> But neuertheleſſe, wee ſhall runne out our race, and come to that period which God hath appointed for vs.</p>
            <p>Thus farre of the <hi>Propoſition.</hi> Now remaineth the <hi>Proofe</hi> thereof, in theſe words of the Text; <hi>In the ſight of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſight of the Lord.</p>
            <p>DAVID proues the death of the Saints to bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious by an argument, not fetched from the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the thing it ſelfe, but taken from without
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6526:26"/>it, to wit, from the teſtimony and authority of God, in theſe words; <hi>In the ſight of the Lord:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay; can it chuſe but bee precious, which the Lord himſelfe approueth, and highly eſteemeth of? It is not poſſible. For hee beſt knowes to diſtinguiſh betweene good and euill, betweene precious and vile. Wherefore if in his iudgement any thing be precious, it muſt needs be true, that it is precious indeed.</p>
            <p>Put the queſtion then; <hi>How commeth it to paſſe, and how might wee be ſure, that the death of the Saints is precious?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the anſwer is giuen: becauſe it pleaſeth God to account it ſo. <hi>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi> It is not long of the Saints, but of Gods meere goodneſſe and mercy vnto them. And becauſe that he of his goodneſſe doth ſo account of it, therefore it is precious, and not for any worthineſſe or deſert of their owne. Neither is this preciouſneſſe of the death of the Saints ſuppoſed and imaginary, but reall and true: the Saints death is truly and really precious. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though man may bee deceiued, and erre in his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet it is otherwiſe with God. It is true of man that in the errour of his iudgement, hee may take a thing to be precious, and ſay, that it is ſo, when there is no ſuch matter, onely becauſe he doth imagine and conceit with himſelfe that ſuch a thing is precious: but God cannot be ſo deceiued. But whatſoeuer he iudgeth and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth precious, it is truly and indeed precious, and it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be otherwiſe. And thus it comes about that the Saints death is precious, and vpon this ground wee are certaine of it. It is precious, and wee know it, becauſe the moſt wiſe God doth account and pronounce it to be precious in his ſight. Thus ye ſee the ſumme of the confirmation.</p>
            <p>To gather profit thereby, we muſt conſider two things; firſt, what manner of argument this is: ſecondly, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication thereof to the matter in hand.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:6526:26"/>
            <p>There be two kindes of proofes, the one called <hi>arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall,</hi> the other <hi>inartificiall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Artificiall proofes</hi> are ſuch as are fetched one way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Artificiall proofes.</note> from the conſideration of the theme or matter it ſelfe which is proued, and of their owne force or nature are able to proue or diſapproue. This proofe of <hi>Dauids</hi> in this place is no ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inartificiall proofes</hi> are ſuch as are fetched from au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,<note place="margin">Inartificiall proofes.</note> either diuine or not diuine. Such a proofe is this that <hi>Dauid</hi> here brings, fetched from the authority of God.</p>
            <p>Now this kinde of prouing of a matter by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of God, howſoeuer it neuer touch the nature of that which is proued, neither explicateth nor illuſtrateth it, yet it begetteth in the minde the greateſt credit and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe to the matter that may bee. For no argument can be deuiſed ſo forcible to procure faith and credit to a matter, as this that is drawne from the authority of God.<note place="margin">Deus per ſe eſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For God is ſimply to bee beleeued for himſelfe, and to doubt of that which he affirmes, is great impiety.</p>
            <p>In this reſpect therefore this teſtimony ſerues for this vſe; for the ſtrengthening of our faith touching the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe of the Saints death. That wee ſhould not doubt nor ſtagger through vnbeleefe, but bee fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that the death of the Saints is precious.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Comfort ouer the death of a Saint.</note>How full of comfort is this, to know vpon a ſure ground, and beyond all exception, euen from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe teſtimony of the Lord God of truth, that the Saints death is precious, and that it is ſo in his ſight, howſoeuer the world doe iudge of it? Can any thing be more comfortable to a Chriſtian ſoule, to ceaſe the mourning thereof for the death of a Saint, and deare childe of God? Let it ſinke into your hearts, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort your ſelues with this meditation. There is, I confeſſe, iuſt cauſe of mourning for the death of the Saints. But where finde we this cauſe? Is it in themſelues? Their life was holy, their courſe is finiſhed, their death is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6526:27"/>their body is at reſt, their ſoule is in heauen, their memoriall is bleſſed, they ſhall ariſe to glory, and bee with Chriſt in heauen for euermore.<note place="margin">The true cauſe of mourning for the Saints death.</note> In reſpect of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues there is no cauſe of mourning. But in reſpect of vs that remaine aliue, there bee many cauſes. For when any of the Saints die, we ſee that all of vs bee encloſed within the curſe of God, becauſe of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne; and ſeeing that, it behooueth vs to feele what we haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and bee aſhamed of ourſelues, and bee touched with the feare of Gods vengeance, and bee ſo wounded therewith, as it may prouoke vs to ſorrow, becauſe of our ſinnes, which we haue committed. Againe, when any of the Saints die, wee loſe a helpe to the peace of our Sion, <hi>I</hi> meane, of our Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, a helpe to the Goſpell, a helpe in the houſe, an interceſſor to God, a louing friend, and a ſhining ſtarre. If it were a thing poſſible, it were beſt for vs to keepe ſuch men ſtill with vs, but for them it is farre better to depart hence, and to bee with Chriſt. For when ſuch are taken from vs, our Lord chaſtiſeth vs, and ſheweth vs a ſigne, that (except we ſpeedily repent) hee is min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to diminiſh his grace vnto vs. The taking away of the beſt men, and of them that doe moſt good in the Church, and amongſt vs, is alwaies a threatning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. And ought wee not to bee grieued at the threatning and feeling of Gods diſpleaſure? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee may iuſtly mourne for the death of the Saints. But yet ſo let vs mourne,<note place="margin">Comfort.</note> that withall wee remember to keepe a meaſure in our mourning, and to pacifie our ſelues with this conſideration, that <hi>their death is precious.</hi> And that God calls them hence to free them from a great deale of miſery, and to doe them a great deale of good.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:6526:27"/>
            <p> In the ſight of the Lord.</p>
            <p>COncerning the application of this proofe to the preſent matter; in as much as <hi>Dauid</hi> affirmes the Saints death to be precious vpon this ground, becauſe it is ſo in Gods ſight, that is to ſay, becauſe God doth ſo eſteeme it; Out of this I gather, that.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>7</label> 
               <hi>Doct.</hi> The right iudgement of matters is to iudge of them as God doth.<note place="margin">To iudge aright, we muſt iudge of things as God doth.</note> They are precious and good that hee approues of, but they are vile and naught, which he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approues.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>The Vſe.</hi> Firſt, how much doth this condemne the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our age? For is not this the nature of the moſt,<note place="margin">Againſt following only the iudgement of the world.</note> that they neuer regard what account God makes of a thing, but only, whether men doe eſteeme of it or no? And if they ſee it in eſteeme with men, is not that enough? Yea they care for no more. They be ſo wedded to the world, that they will neuer looke whether God doe like or diſlike that which they fancie, or ſet themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt: and they be ſo blinde and obſtinate, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is taught them, they will neither ſee nor learne, nor at no hand admit any other iudgement of matters, than that which they haue receiued from this wicked world. But let them looke to it; they that now follow the world, and build ſo wholly vpon the likings of the multitude, ſhall hereafter periſh with the world. For the friends of the world muſt fare as the world doth. Oh how much better were it to iudge otherwiſe than the world doth; than now to agree with this preſent euill world, and in the life to come to partake of her plagues!</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this ſerues excellently to direct vs to iudge aright of matters.<note place="margin">To ſhew vs the rule of iudging aright.</note> We muſt not preſently like and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend a thing, becauſe men generally doe like it: nor we muſt not preſently condemne that, which moſt men doe diſlike. For as our Sauiour ſaith:<note place="margin">Luke 16.15.</note> 
               <hi>That which is highly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6526:28"/>eſteemed among men, is abomination in the ſight of God.</hi> As namely, the counterfeit holineſſe of the Phariſies. So then there be ſome things that God abhorres, which men highly eſteeme of. And thinke the like on the contrary, that there be ſome things againe, which men deſpiſe, which God highly eſteemes of, as holineſſe, puritie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie in preaching the Word in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, powerfull applying of the doctrine, and ſuch like. Now therefore if we will iudge aright, wee muſt learne what things be approued with God, and make account of them; and what things he diſapproues, and diſlike and condemne them; and neuer regard the iudgements of men to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, is the right iudgement of things to iudge of them as God doth?<note place="margin">See that thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of matters do agree with Gods.</note> Then if we beleeue this, as our duty is, it cannot poſſibly be, but that we ſhall make more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the iudgement of God concerning all things, than moſt men doe; and accordingly will we giue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence not only in vſing the meanes whereby to haue our iudgements to agree with Gods iudgement, but alſo in learning what things be in eſteeme with him, that wee alſo may haue the ſame in like eſteeme with vs: and eſteeme all other things, which hee eſteemeth not, as droſſe and dung, howſoeuer the ſame be in eſteeme with the world.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, this truth ſerueth for the comfort of the children of God,<note place="margin">Comfort againſt contempt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit for iudging of matters as God doth.</note> againſt the contempt and loſſe of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in the world, for making much of ſome things which God eſteemeth, but the world regardeth not, and for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting light by ſome other things, which God eſteemeth not, but yet the world doth admire and highly commend them. Thus it often commeth to paſſe through the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe iudgements of men, and their ſelfe-pleaſing and ſelfe-will, that vertuous and godly people ſhall be light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regarded and out of credit euen for regarding that which the moſt care not for, and for not regarding that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6526:28"/>which they admire. But be not diſcouraged. For as long as thy iudgement doth agree with the iudgement of God, and theirs doth not, thy iudgement is better than theirs. And as much contempt and loſſe of credit as thou bringeſt vpon thy ſelfe by this meanes with the world: ſo much honour and good credit thou winneſt with all them that doe truly feare God. And the time will come, when thy iudgement ſhall be approued, and theirs reiected. Conſider of it, and take comfort.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE OCCASION OF this meeting.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow as touching the occaſion of this our meeting, this firſt I ſay, that that which the Holy Ghoſt doth here teach vs to hold of the death of the Saints in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Chriſtian charitie doth binde vs to conceiue concerning our worthy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther departed in the faith of Chriſt. For if the death of Gods Saints be precious in his ſight, and our aſſured hope be, that he was one of his Saints; why ſhould wee not conceiue aſſured hope that his death was precious, and that his ſoule is bleſſed? Now that charitie bindeth vs thus to conceiue of him I will make it manifeſt. For beſides that there is no euidence to the contrary, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie euermore iudgeth the beſt: wee haue alſo ſufficient euidence, wherupon to conclude according to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of charitie, that he liued and died a Saint. I ſay, according to the iudgement of charitie. For as the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of certaintie belongeth vnto the Lord: ſo the iudgement of charitie belongeth vnto vs, that ſerue the Lord.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore take a briefe view of ſuch fruits (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6526:29"/>to which alone, being charitably interpreted, true charitie doth iudge) I ſay of ſuch fruits and ſignes as haue appeared both in the time of his health, and alſo in the time of his ſickneſſe vntill his death.</p>
               <p>Firſt then,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Cleybrooke</hi> was <hi>1.</hi> A zealous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of the true Faith.</note> to beginne with his Religion: he was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Popiſh nor Schiſmaticall, nor any way factious, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he a Neuter or Nullifidian, which is too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a vice, but a profeſſed Proteſtant and an open Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour of the true faith of Chriſt. Neither was he a cold or lukewarme profeſſour (as many are, who haue no care of Religion) but a forward and zealous one: one that had his Fathers name written in his forehead,<note place="margin">Reuel. 14.1.</note> as the faithfull are deſcribed in the Reuelation. For hee would make it appeare vpon euery iuſt occaſion, of what Religion hee was, and without feare of any man maintaine the truth, and ſuch points of euery mans dutie as belong thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Neither could hee endure to heare it trodden vnder foot, nor any to bee ſpoken againſt for maintaining thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> A great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencer of Gods Name.</note>He did ſo feare that glorious and fearefull name of the <hi>Lord his God,</hi> that he ſtucke to put the paper, in which he ſaw any of the titles of the bleſſed Trinitie written, to any diſhonourable vſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> A diligent fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenter of religious Exerciſes.</note>He was a diligent frequenter of the holy Exerciſes of Religion, and a furtherer thereof by his trauell, credit, money, and other waies; and a conſtant Communicant according to the order of the place, from moneth to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. Yea, and when he was not able to trauell a foot to the Church, he vſed helpes that he might not be abſent. And as he did himſelfe, ſo he cauſed his houſhold to doe. So that he and his houſhold became an example of fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting their Church, and often receiuing of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> A true friend to faithfull Preachers.</note>He loued, reueren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, and fauoured any faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Preachers of Gods word. And whereas dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diligence in preaching is a cauſe why many cannot
<pb facs="tcp:6526:29"/>brooke the Preacher, this was one ſpecial thing which drew his affection vnto him. He loued Preachers for labouring painfully in the Word and Doctrine. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtles rule;<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and to eſteeme them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry highly in loue for their workes ſake.</hi> As touching my ſelfe, I doe with thankfulneſſe acknowledge the greatneſſe of his loue manifeſted towards mee diuers waies, and moſt of all towards his latter end. And this I dare auouch, that the Saints of the Lord can be diſcerned by no one ſigne better, than by a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Miniſters of the Word. For our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaith; <hi>He that receiueth whomſoeuer I ſend,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 13.20. Luke 10.16.</note> 
                  <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me; and hee that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me.</hi> As he that deſpiſeth a Miniſter in reſpect of his calling, and faithfull paines in his Miniſtery, doth euidently bewray himſelfe neither to haue any grace nor yet to deſire any, becauſe the grace which either he hath or can deſire, ordinarily is attained by the Miniſtery, as I could ſhew at large; ſo hee that loueth and reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth a Miniſter for his workes ſake, (as this worthy man did) he doth ſhew that he hath found the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Word to be the power of God to his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>5.</hi> A louer of the Saints.</note>He honoured the Saints, and made much of them that were truly religious: but vile and naughtie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in whom was no religion nor knowledge of God, were odious in his ſight, and their fond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, and vaine mirth and paſtime were a vexation to his heart. Which is one good note of a childe of God; as the Holy Ghoſt doth witneſſe, ſaying: that he ſhall abide in Gods Tabernacle,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.1, 4.</note> and ſhall dwell in his holy hill; <hi>In whoſe eyes a vile perſon is contemned; but he honoureth them that feare the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>6.</hi> A man gracious in his talke.</note>He delighted much to conferre of points of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and of the preſent eſtate, and duties of a true Chriſtian. And in his conferences hee would often
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6526:30"/>complaine of the rifeneſſe of ſinne, of the negligence and bad doings of diuers in the Miniſtery, of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of the due execution of iuſtice for ſundry or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary offences, of the corruption of his owne fleſh, and of his owne vntowardneſſe and dulneſſe in Gods ſeruice; and inueigh ſeriouſly and to good purpoſe againſt exceſſiue drinking, and other vices of the times.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>7.</hi> Patient vnder the Croſſe.</note>He was patient vnder the croſſe, of which he hath had much and long experience, more waies then one. For it pleaſed the Lord to exerciſe him certain yeeres before his death, with diuers temptations both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and outwardly: in all which hee abode con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, ſubmitting himſelfe quietly to the will of God, making vſe of all to the glory of his name, and being ſo farre from being diſcouraged, that his zeale, his loue of the truth, his patience, and other vertues en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed ſtill to his dying day.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>8.</hi> Sober, and graue.</note>He was a ſober, graue, diſcreet, frugall, temperate, and chaſte man. Hee contented himſelfe with plaine apparrell, and neither affected coſtlineſſe, nor new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions therein. He went alwaies plainer, and a great deale more meane, than many others, which in eſtate were farre inferiour to himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>9.</hi> Without ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>He was not ambitious. He coueted no titles of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, nor places of publike ſeruice: but wondred at others, what they ſaw therein, to couet and deſire the ſame; and contented himſelfe with his owne eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>10.</hi> Not high min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note>He was nothing high minded, but made himſelfe equall to them of the lower ſort; according to the Apoſtles rule:<note place="margin">Rom. 12.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Be of the ſame minde one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Minde not high things, but condeſcend to men of low eſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>11.</hi> A louing huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</note>He ſhewed alwaies great loue and fidelitie to his wife.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:6526:30"/>
               <p>He was a very carefull father for the godly liuing and well-doing of his children.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>12.</hi> A carefull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>13.</hi> A vertuous maſter.</note>He baniſhed from among his ſeruants many horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vices (which as they be vſuall now adaies in great Families, ſo no doubt they will pull downe the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgements of God vpon them) I meane, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and ſwaggering, and ſuch other enormities; and he ſo gouerned, admoniſhed, and ordered them, that ſome haue departed out of his houſe, more godly, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, frugall, and honeſter men, than they were before they came vnto him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>14.</hi> A perf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rmer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nſel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>f good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at home.</note>He performed himſelfe the ordinary duties of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in his houſe at home, if no Preacher were preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>15.</hi> Prouident in his buſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſes.</note>Hee was wiſe and prouident in managing his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and left none of his bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ineſſes at ſix and ſeuen, but was a carefull ouerſeer of all himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>16.</hi> Bountifull to the poore.</note>Hee was plentifull in releeuing his poore neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; a peaceable liuer, and one that put vp a great number of treſpaſſes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>17.</hi> Peaceable.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>18.</hi> Able and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to giue good aduice.</note>He afforded his counſell willingly for their beſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection that ſtood in need of it, and eſpecially for the good eſtate of the place and Pariſh in which he liued; vnto the people whereof, and to many others, he bare good affection. Neither did he manifeſt his affection in word and tongue onely, but by ſhewing himſelfe forward in any good cauſe for their inſtruction and profit any manner of way. The truth whereof, if we did not ſufficiently ſee, whileſt wee enioyed him: I doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we ſhall too well feele, by wanting of him now he is gone.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>19.</hi> No nouice in vertue.</note>Neither was hee a nouice in the practiſe of any of theſe things, but a well experienced ſouldier of many yeeres ſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>20.</hi> Conſtant to the end in well-doing.</note>And vnto all this was added conſtancie and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance vnto the end. His well-doing was not by fits,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6526:31"/>nor for a while only, as it hath proued by ſome, but till the end of his daies. Witneſſe his bountie and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall contribution to haue the Word often prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. Neither was hee weary of that which hee did. Nay he was ſo farre from being weary, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding both the death of one of them that ioyned with him, and that the vnfaithfulneſſe of ſome, which haue fallen from their word, had cauſed him to be at more charge, than at the firſt he had thought of; yet of his owne accord hee charged himſelfe ſomewhat further, than his owne compartners in that buſineſſe did know of. And being motioned to ſome courſe, whereby to be diſcharged from all, he ſpake no word to approue of it, but all to the contrary. Then it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſignified vnto him, that ſome further courſe muſt be taken, and what was expected, his anſwer was, that it was as little as could be.<note place="margin">Auguſt. 5.1622.</note> And all this, not long before his laſt ſickneſſe. By which it appeares how his minde was ſetled not to faint in well doing, but to continue to the end.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>21.</hi> Mindfull to ſet his houſe in order before his ſickneſſe. Hee was taken in the night with a dead palſie in halfe his body: on <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. 15. 1622.</hi>
                  </note>Before his laſt ſickneſſe he had made his will and ſet his houſe in order. But in the time of that ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which was about the ſpace of nine daies, hee had but little vſe of his ſpeech; neither was he able to expreſſe himſelfe in diuers things to the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his friends, which appeared by certaine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens to be a great griefe vnto him. And becauſe of this, we doutleſſe want much of that teſtimony of his faith which he would haue giuen vs, if he had had the liberty of his ſpeech.<note place="margin">The godly ſpeeches vnderſtood in his ſickneſſe.</note> But yet ſome few things he vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered now and then which were vnderſtood; as that a certaine Miniſter which was with him all the time of his ſickneſſe, <hi>had done him much good,</hi> which when the Miniſter heard, hee entreated him to render the whole praiſe thereof vnto God alone, who bleſſeth the weake endeuours of his ſeruants in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6526:31"/>for the good of his people. Which thing hee alſo did, as appeared by the preſent motion of his hands and eies. Againe hee ſaid; <hi>that God accepteth the heart, and the deſires thereof.</hi> And when he was told that his words, which were imperfect to vs, were perfect to God, and that God vnderſtood what hee did deſire; he anſwered, <hi>yea:</hi> and gaue vs ſuch tokens as he was able, that hee knew ſo much. Further he ſaid; <hi>God giueth vs ſome refreſhing and reioycing, that we may be able to paſſe thorow:</hi> expreſſing (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue) the comfort of his owne ſoule, which God gaue him in his extremitie. And his laſt ſpeech that I vnderſtood, was this, that <hi>wee are leſſe than nothing before him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>22.</hi> Hee was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of praier in his ſickneſſe.</note>In all his ſickneſſe, from the firſt morning thereof, (for he was taken in the night) hee was very willing and deſirous to haue praiers duely and often vnto the Lord. Sometimes he himſelfe would call for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this duty. Hee deſired vs to pray vnto God for him and with him.<note place="margin">He died of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexie On <hi>Auguſt. 24. 1622.</hi>
                  </note> And when the motion was made vnto him, while his ſenſe continued with him, if it were deferred but neuer ſo little, for any cauſe whatſoeuer, he himſelfe would haſten it; ſaying, <hi>When? when?</hi> as he was able.</p>
               <p>I am not able to ſpeake al, which of ſo worthy a man might truly be ſpoken. And in that which I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, you are not to vnderſtand me, as though I went about to maintaine, that he had no infirmities, or that he neuer failed in any particulars: for alas,<note place="margin">Iames 3.2.</note> 
                  <hi>in many things wee offend all.</hi> And highly is that man to bee commended, whoſe generall courſe is ſuch, as I haue now ſet downe, although he faile through infirmity in many particulars.</p>
               <p>And the things conſidered, and weighed in the ballance of charity, which haue beene ſpoken, wee may be bold to conclude according to the iudgement
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6526:32"/>of charity, that hee is in the number of thoſe Saints whoſe death in this place, the Holy Ghoſt pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth precious in the ſight of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Now what remaineth? but firſt that thoſe whom he hath left behinde him, who in his life time were the neereſt and deareſt vnto him, doe ſet before their eies ſo godly a patterne, and ſtriue by all meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble him to the vtmoſt. It was <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> requeſt when <hi>Elijah</hi> was taken from him, that a double portion of his ſpirit might bee vpon him.<note place="margin">2 King. 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Aske</hi> (ſaid <hi>Elijah</hi>) <hi>what I ſhall doe for thee, before I bee taken away from thee. And Eliſha ſaid, I pray thee, let a double portion of thy ſpirit be vpon me.</hi> And when <hi>Dauid</hi> had giuen order, and <hi>Solomon</hi> was made king, <hi>Dauids</hi> ſeruants, (as ſaith the text,) came to bleſſe their Lord king <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> ſaying;<note place="margin">1 King. 1.47.</note> 
                  <hi>God make the name of Solomon better than thy name, and make his throne greater than thy throne. And the king bowed himſelfe vpon the bed,</hi> ſhewing his good acceptance of his ſeruants words. Euen ſo wiſh I, that the vertues of the deceaſed may bee doubled vpon the liuing. And I beſeech them all by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, that the remembrance of the things, which (as I was able in reſpect of mine owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) I haue now rehearſed, and of all other good things, which they haue knowne and ſeene to bee in him, farre better than my ſelfe, may be ſo imprinted in their hearts that they may neuer be forgotten, but that in the whole courſe of their life they may imitate and follow them, and adde more thereunto, that as they inherit his lands and goods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo they may inherit his reputation and good report<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that with much more honour and greater fame than hee did enioy it himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Finally it reſteth, that both they and wee all, which remaine aliue, and are left behinde him, doe humbly beſeech the Lord to ſanctifie vs wholly, and to grant
<pb facs="tcp:6526:32"/>vs that the life which wee now liue in the fleſh, wee may liue by the faith of the Sonne of God, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer God ſhall call vs, our death may bee precious, and we may ſleepe in Ieſus: and ſleeping in him wee may be brought with him, and be glorified with him by the full fruition of God himſelfe the chiefeſt good: To which moſt gracious and moſt glorious God, the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, be all praiſe, honour, and glory, both now and for euermore. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="erratum">
            <head>Erratum.</head>
            <p>CHriſtian reader, at <hi>page 11. line 26.</hi> for <hi>Pſal.</hi> read <hi>Pſalmes.</hi> And the reſt is well and truly printed from the beginning to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Giue all the glory to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6526:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:6526:7"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:6526:7"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:6526:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:6526:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:6526:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:6526:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:6526:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6526:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:6526:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
